<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>阿掖山：一个博客</title>
    <description>阿掖山：一个博客</description>
    <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="mountaye.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 22:22:12 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 22:22:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>马普所·非平衡态系统中的集体过程·语音转录 | 02. Stochastic Process</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;这次的内容大致分为两部分，一是继续将朗之万方程推广，另一部分是主方程。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-stochastic-process&quot;&gt;2. Stochastic Process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again five minutes late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today i would like uh to begin say the methodological part of the lecture and uh to begin to introduce some of the methods that we need to describe non-equilibrium systems. And if we describe non-equilibrium systems then of course that’s pretty broad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you look at systems that come into your mind if you think about non-equilibrium systems epidemics biology and these systems are generally very small. You might think about for example the number of infected people and race or the number of new infection in infections and racing a certain day is maybe what do we have 10 or so. Yeah it’s a small number yeah and chance of fluctuations have a large influence on this number you know if you have in a small tone if you have one COVID case and this one person recovers then you have a child then you have a change by 100. So in small systems small changes have large consequences large statistical consequences. In other words we have strong fluctuations. The same of course also holds true in biology where uh if you look at the number of transcripts of a given gene you know in a given cell then it’s typically just a few thousand or. So it’s not 10 to the 20 and 10 to the power of uh 26 usually are used to in a gas or a magnet from statistical physics. These are rather small numbers and we cannot just say that such systems are completely described by the evolution of some average or deterministic evolution of some average quantity. So we need to start looking at fluctuations around these averages can be very important and are very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to this end let me share the screen. There we go okay you can share the screen unfortunately you also simply see um the um toolbars is that correct you can can you see the two balls ah something is different than last time. Okay. I hope that is not doesn’t bother you too much and i don’t know what’s the reason for this yeah okay. That’s at least it seems to be working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-1&quot;&gt;Slide 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When i talk about fluctuations then uh that means of course that we have to describe these non-equilibrium systems that i was talking about in terms of stochastic processes. That means taking into account the stochastic stochasticity that isn’t used by the small size of many of these systems. And the field of mathematics and physics that deals with such processes are is called stochastic processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now many of you will be familiar with stochastic processes particularly those on the phd level. I nevertheless want to give you a brief introduction to stochastic processes today. So That we’re all on the same level and can start moving on to field theory and other topics from next week onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is a stochastic process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stochastic process is just the collection of random variables. These very variable variables that take a random variable that at a random value that is has an index that we call the time t. You know this is the stochastic process and uh there are of course different all kinds of stochastic processes.The simplest one but not the simplest one but the ones that we’re usually dealing with in physics just for mathematical simplicity are markov processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markov processes have the property that they lack memory. That means that the state probability to find the system in a certain state for example to have five infections and on november 11. yeah this probability only depends on the previous time in the system but not on times before that yeah and that is denoted by these conditional probabilities here in principle you can think that the state of the system at a certain time t i depends explicitly on all of the previous times. It remembers what was going on in the past. Now the markov process is a process where the state of the probability to find the system in a certain state only depends on the state that it had at the previous time stack. These markov processes don’t have memory and that makes them simple to handle and in many situations uh this markov approximation is actually a very good approximation and a necessary approximation that we need to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal that we have in the theory of stochastic processes is that we want to find the probability that our random variable x takes a certain value that i denote by lowercase x at a given time t. That’s what we call p of x and t the probability that a random variable takes a value x at a time t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we get this probability? the two approaches&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first approach i introduced last time. That’s the approach the langevan equation and that is a project where we also have a look later in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can just take a look at specific realizations of the stochastic process you know a specific realization of this stochastic process that is then given by this langevin equation and then we can sample many of these these realizations and define an appropriate statistical ensemble and from this ensemble we can then calculate our probabilities our moments and other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach is the langevin approach and this is based on calculating the trajectories of individual realizations and last time i showed you this approach in the context of brownian motion. If you think about brown emotion then another name pops up in your head and this other name is einstein yeah so einstein had a different approach to brown emotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He didn’t model individual trajectories. What he was looking for was to directly consider the time evolution of the probability density p of x and t yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the goal in the second approach is then to find a differential equation that describes this time evolution yea. So this is the second approach to stochastic processes and we’ll have a brief look at each of these approaches in this lecture lecture today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-2&quot;&gt;Slide 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at the first approach. The langevan equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The larger equation is a specific case of a stochastic differential equation and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general form you can see on the top here that basically looks at looks like the larger equation that you know of course yeah the time evolution of some random variable x is given by a deterministic part plus a stochastic part and this stochastic part has this psi term that we were looking at last time this noise term this stochastic force that takes random value at e at each instant of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the stochastic part can also have complicated forms but to make our life easier we classify these terms and these forms here this is a functional form of b of x e and then we have two broad categories of stochastic differential equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first case is if this b is just constant then the strength of the noise does not depend on the current state of the system. Noise is then called additive it comes on top of what we have as the state of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second case you could have is that this b is not constant but depends on x. If this b pre-factor here depends on depends on x then the strength of the noise is related to the current state of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is then called multiplicative noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a multiplicative noise is for example an epidemic. If you have an epidemic and the epidemic virus goes extinct to the population that it doesn’t come back for a very long time. That means if this x here the concentration of this virus the population is zero then the stochastic force is also very small or even zero you know that that is just one of the prime examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These so-called absorbing states where you go extinct for example and then you don’t have any noise anymore no because the thing just disappears and it doesn’t come back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then that’s one of the prime examples is absorbing stuff it’s always says one of the prime examples of multiplicative noise and a very important class of stochastic processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now write this general form of the stochastic differential equation in a differential form as the principle can also do with ordinary differential equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in this differential form rewrite it this way it’s a little bit uh you know it’s almost trivial we get the dt here it finishes infinitesimal time interval and we get a d w of t here yeah and this is already the first indication that differentials and integrals and stochastic differential equations and stochastic processes are not that easy because we don’t have the x but we have some dw of t that is the w of t is called the WEINER PROCESS and this is just defined by in differential form that the differential of this weiner process is equal to the value of psi of t times dt or in integral form that’s equal to the total contributions of the noise of the cumulative stochastic force until a certain time t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can formulate formally just integrate this equation you know we just integrate over time and then we formally get a solution of this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-3&quot;&gt;slide 3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just integrate over time and here on the right hand side we formally have some integral over this vena process all over this differential stochastic force here dw of s you know and one of the central questions and stochastic processes is that the fundament of stochastic process is what is this integral here yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is this integral here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we can do and i’ll show you later that it’s important uh how to define this integral so-called stochastic integral one way to look at this is to take the time domain and cut it into small pieces yeah that’s called a partition n pi of n of time and we cut it into small pieces into small intervals a number of n intervals and then we just say that this stochastic integral over some function f is the limit of infinitely small intervals and then we do something similar as in the normal riemann integral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That the usual integral that we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say that this is just the function evaluated at a specific time in the summer in this interval times basically the size of this integral which is the discrete form of this differential. The question is this is some kind of a weighted sum yeah you’re on the right-hand side and the weights because w is again a stochastic variable yeah are themselves random variables. This integral again is a stochastic integral and the result of this integral is again is to test a random variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see here on the bottom right. We have this interval t j the sort of the previous time point t j plus one the next time point and then somewhere in the in the middle we evaluate our function and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-4&quot;&gt;slide 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think that if we go to the limit where this interval here becomes very small. Infinitely small like we do in usual calculus then it doesn’t really matter where we evaluate the function you know by the stochastic processes things are not that easy it actually matters where you evaluate this interval this integral and that’s what i will show you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By just looking at two specific choices of this integral there are two specific choices of where we evaluate the function when we integrate it yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left hand side uh we’ll do a little calculation where we just set uh this function this point where we evaluate the integral to be on the left end of the integral and on the right hand we’ll evaluate the integral by taking the function on the right end of each interval and as a test function we just integrate over this we know process wt yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This calculation is rather simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We take a look at the average over i’ll just write down this integral not j equals one to n w t j w t j plus 1 minus w t j. That’s this integral evaluated at the left hand side yeah and then we just say okay. This average is a linear function. We have j equal one to end and the sum moves out of the average wtj w tj plus one minus w t j.We can factorize it because of the independence of these w j equals 1 to n w t j w t j plus 1 minus w [Music] tj.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep was there a question okay um yes. Here um the dj star is the point that we have the freedom to choose either on the left or right hand side exactly. This was here on the previous slide. On the previous side we had this formula um yeah and. We’re just writing down this formula here where our function f is w and we evaluate t j star. So here we have the choice where to put it on the rest on the left boundary of the interval yeah it’s just the same formula we just plug in what we get if we if this tj star is equal to tj and if our function f is equal to w yeah and we just do that to give you an example what you get when you integrate when you do statistic integration yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no biological application also it’s just a mathematical exercise to show you uh that you get weird results with stochastic processes and on in this case here this second integral here is just equal to zero because the the differences between integral between time integrands are the difference between these values of w at different time points is a random gaussian variable with mean zero because our soi you know that was what we had here originally here yes is random our sign is a random as a stochastic as a random variable that is normally distributed opposite gaussian distribution with mean zero yeah and this is basically right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average is also zero yes uh right at this place i would like to ask in the previous slide um yes. We initially started with uh x which was our primary random variable and the evolution of which we’re trying to figure out then we said that um even b b psi was the stochastic part or the random part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B in itself can be any function it’s not a stochastic function it can be for example x squared also you know. This in itself is not stochastic but because you multiply it to the stochastic function sine or this random variable psi this whole second part becomes yeah. The b is just uh for example in the random and the brownian motion the b was the strength of the noise and that was what we calculated we call it recorded a and it was just a number that represented the strength of the node no but it can have more complicated forms it can be x squared or something else yeah. X squared exponential of x square root of x whatever you know. That in principle this can be any function of x and even of t if you want to make it really complicated yes and nicely speaking we can say that the the fact the reason that we’re calling a x a of x t as deterministic is because we we ha we know um we know the trend of a with respect to x and t i believe speaking it could be anything but we know the trend yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way yes yes exactly yeah. Another way to see it is if you say no we don’t have just 100 cases of code but 10 to the 26 yeah like a huge number of cases or you look all the x is the number of particles in this room for example yeah then the stochastic part would vanish. Because then you also saw okay there might be at every second there might be a few molecules going in and out of this room yeah but if you have 10 to the 26 molecules in total yeah then you don’t need to worry about that then the a will completely describe our system that means it’s essentially deterministic it’s not the fluctuation the noise that we get here is small compared to the actual value of x.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we call this okay yes yes that’s the scale of the system the scale all the sides of the system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;yes the xi typically disappears if you make your system larger and larger. Of course there are counter examples like exotic counter examples but typically you could think that the psi at some point disappear if you make your resistance larger and larger it’s like the central limit theory right. If you have a large number of observations you know then at some point your uh your measurements that you say will be uh still follow a distribution but will be sharply p around the average and then it’s fine if you just look at the average and not at the variations and that’s also what we typically do in statistical physics you know if you have 10 to 20 to the power of 26 particles yeah then uh you can neglect typically fluctuations around 10 to the 26 yeah if you have 20 10 to the 26 times plus 100 or so that doesn’t matter that. That’s why we call this part stochastic and the other part okay and it’s it seems a pretty pretty random right. That we put w t uh equal to f of t it’s completely random right it’s completely random uh yes it is pedagogically not random yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We you would see here that this is off because what i just wrote this is just 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just an example integral and I can calculate the same thing on the right hand side and on the right-hand side we evaluate the integral on the right hand side not. So we have j equals one to n w t j plus one w t tj plus one minus w t j. and now we do a little trick that means that we here subtract zero yeah we subtract the zero that we have here on the left hand side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that this is zero and we can just subtract uh what we have on the left hand side w t j w t j plus one minus w to j how we know that this is zero and if you plug that in and move it into the average then we see that this whole thing on top will be equal to j equals one to n w t j plus 1 minus w t j squared and if we just evaluate that uh taking into account again that this is a weiner process and the difference is basically follows a normal random variable we get that this is equal to j equals 1 to n t j plus 1 minus t j and then only the last boundary terms will survive and this is equal to t minus p0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is not zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just to show you that if i evaluate this integral on the left hand side and on the right hand side then we get different results and we need to decide on one specific conventions and in the fields of course there are multiple conventions not just one for example two common choices first choice is the so-called ito integral and as each in this ito integral we say that this t star j is equal to t j.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what you have on the left hand side we evaluate the into the the function and the integral on the left and hand side of these intervals yeah and in this lecture we will usually use the ito integral the second choice is the so-called stratanovic integral yeah and this just means that we evaluate this function in the middle of this interval t j plus 1 minus tj divided by 2 plus tj.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s the middle of this integral and you always have if you do if you work on stochastic differential equation you always have to say in which which kind of stochastic interval integral you’re using ito or strotonovich and depending on your choice your results will be different difficult different mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s always important to state which choice of this interval of this stochastic integral you’re using because the results as you saw in these two examples will be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-5&quot;&gt;Slide 5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was our first let’s say glimpse into stochastic calculus and that already showed that stochastic calculus is not quite as straightforward as our usual calculus and another manifestation of this is that the usual rules of calculus are also different for stochastic processes and one important example is the chain rule in stochastic takers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the chain room we want to evaluate a quantity that is some function f of x of t like a variable transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s have a look how if we transform such a make a variable transformation of a stochastic variable what we will get and i wouldn’t show you that if not something interesting or at least unexpected would be the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s first do a taylor expansion you know just taylor expansion. That we get that del f over del t dt you know plus just taylor expansion del f over del x dx plus second order df squared over stop working i think i have to pair the pen again okay let’s see if that works okay. Second order x squared dx squared oh it’s just taylor expansion of course we can continue that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have our dx here in this expansion and we just substitute substitute the langevin the equation in differential form for the x yeah and then what we get is that the first term does not have any dx dt dt you know plus now we have our dx and we substitute the largemouth or the stochastic differential equation in differential form a plus dt plus sorry a times dt plus b times dw and i’ll run into problems space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second term of course becomes a little bit more complicated and this is a second derivative delta x squared and we have to substitute the launch of the equation with this dx squared on the previous line and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collect the terms that’s second order term in time squared plus continue here 2 a e d t w plus e squared b w squared plus higher orders and. What we will use is we uh only want to take into account the highest orders in time yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you differentiate what is what we do we usually it’s like a linear approximation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We take only into account the linear order in dt and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second step we we collect these dts and what we get is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To highest order in dt del f over del t plus a del f over del x plus b squared over 2 del squared f over del x squared times dt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then that’s the highest order in dt plus b del f over del x d w.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s called ITO’S FORMULA and what you can see is that the chain rule is not as convenient as in using the usual uh non-stochastic calculus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you have to think if you make a transformation that you get quite a few new terms just because you’re dealing with fantastic processes one term has not been taken the term with two a b dt dw that is also linear in dt let me see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two adt yes this is also here you have it where’s the other one uh the next one which has pre-factored to way b it’s t d w and d w scales with dt squared exactly sorry square square root dt square root of dt exactly yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That that’s what i should say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dw scales with the square root of dt and the reason is that this dw is essentially something like this brownie motion and if you look at this browning motion from last time then you see that the typical distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That you travel scales with the square root of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard deviation increases with the square root of time and this is how you can see that roughly this dw scales the square root of dt yeah and that’s why uh as you said uh this term looks like it like you know okay this just yes thank you just just to show you that um um.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is uh just to show you that the chain rule in stochastic processes is a little bit more difficult like many other things as well as stochastic processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What i should say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that what i would suggest is that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-6--7&quot;&gt;slide 6 &amp;amp; 7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have your examples and what i will do is i will leave the examples to the end of the lecture until we’re done with the methods and depending on how we’re doing with time you’ll have these examples then in the notes that i’ll upload to the web page and by the way i should give you the password that’s the password is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My my last name and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With it after that you can open the lecture notes and then you can have a look at the example at the examples or we will have time at the end of the lectures to go through these examples just because some of you have already heard stochastic processes for the 10th time and others are still maybe undergrad or graduate students uh that’s here suggested processes for the first time and um.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are trying to find a little way uh of going through this topic here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All for Of course a very nice epidemic example again yeah i’ll leave it for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And uh you’ll see you’ll be either do that at the end of the lecture or when we um you can see it on the slides that are on the website yeah that’s just how you how how how it is to do calculations with these larger equations with this e2 formula and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-8&quot;&gt;Slide 8&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we have the second approach in stochastic processes and the second approach dealt with finding a differential equation for the time evolution of the probability to find a system at a certain time t that is in a certain state x at a certain time t. and for now we write that in the form we have some initial conditions i suppose that the system was at some initial condition initial state x naught at time t naught given that this that we have this initial conditions we’re looking at the conditional probability to then find the system in the state x at time t and at the first step you can look if you look at the plot on the left hand side if you ask what is the probability to end up in x if i started on x naught then what we do is we can sum up all the different paths that the system took to get from x naught via some intermediary state x prime to x. And each of these paths has certain probabilities. What is the probability to be in this state given that we started here this red line. This is given by this here the conditional probability to be in x prime at t prime given that i started at x naught and t naught you know and then the second part of this diagram is what is the probability to end up in x if i was previously in any of these states x prime we can sum up these contributions we can sum over all different parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have one trajectory here one way through this uh through these parts here one diff one specific trajectory yeah then this is given by this multi uh the product of these two probabilities we are going from here to here and from here to here and then we sum up of all possible parts and what we get is this formula here that’s called the CHAPMAN CHROMOGOROV EQUATION.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That just says what i just said in words in the continuum form if i want to know the probability that i will that i’m an x at time t given that i started at x naught and t naught then i just have to integrate or sum up all the possible parts all the possible parts this system can take and weight these paths by their probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what is in this chapman komagorov formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you go through all possible paths and sum up the total probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chapman called mogoro formula is not very convenient it seems like it solves the problem of getting p of x and t but it’s not very convenient in practical purposes and to do to be able to calculate this p f of x and t more conveniently we rather want a differential equation that describes the time evolution of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that was the that was the written notes version of the transition here of the slide transition it was very fancy. So what is the time evolution of this probability p of x t. We’re trying to get a differential equation that tells us what’s happening. And this differential equation is again are picturized here on the left hand side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do lengthy calculations to get it but the idea is pretty simple if i want to know what the change in probability of being in a state x at time t then i have to have to look at two different contributions yeah one contribution is what goes into the state from the left hand side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the flux of probability into this state and then on the other hand i have the contribution that i have to subtract subtract from that that is what is the probability to go out of the state yeah that’s the green stuff here you know and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time evolution of this probability of being in state x attack time t is given by a balance between what comes in and what goes out yeah and this balance is described by a so-called master equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This master equation has the form of the quite complicated form like here on the left hand side we sum up all the contributions that go into this state but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose more convenient notation to describe these conditional probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the rate of going from x prime to x here the red thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That the rate of the transition rates are going transition rate times the probability that i was an x prime in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the right hand side we have to subtract i think that’s supposed to be minus if i’m not wrong no we have to subtract what flows out of this state you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the probability that i’m in state x in the first place times the rate w of going out of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the w. How do i get out of this state or at which rate do i get out of this state and these transition rates w that’s basically also a transition matrix a large matrix these transition rates define the stochastic transitions between states in our systems and that’s what you typically have in the first place and you can typically have these rates based on fatalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say phenomenological arguments the master equation is typically a phenomenological equation where you define these rates based on simple modeling assumptions that you make about your system for example what is the probability that i have one more covert case than yesterday and that would be one such as position rate how does that depend on the number of cases i already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That that would go into this transition rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This master equation again it’s a little bit simple it’s technological you have to balance these two contributions it’s a little bit simpler but it’s still hardly ever solvable yeah and numerically that’s pretty easy it’s solvable actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much part of this lecture because it’s a numerical thing um let me give you some flashy color this one here uh if you want to have simple stochastic simulations you can solve this uh equation by using something called the GILLESPIE ALGORITHM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you just google that like you’ll find a ton of literature on this the very simple algorithm to solve approximately or to sample trajectories from master equations and with this you can basically if you know how to program in a few hours you can have a stochastic simulation but analytically you know this is not this master equation is not that convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have to make approximations to this master equation.  i’m sorry is this example come to that in the end yeah where’s the equation okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-9&quot;&gt;Slide 9&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;skipped :-(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-10--11&quot;&gt;slide 10 &amp;amp; 11&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way you do that is basically do you do a taylor expansion no that means that you have a taylor expansion in your state x yeah you expanded x or you expand x in these transitions and the sizes of your transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you assume that is del is that is delta x here the jumps that you make in the system are very small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That the only ever increment for example the number of cases in very small steps and then you can tailor expand in this in these uh steps here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example delta x x prime is the previous state x is the current state and then you assume that the change from the previous state to the next state is always small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a continuum approximation and what you can then do is you can formally write on a taylor expansion of the master equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do a lot of bookkeeping of terms and what you get is something that then in the end indeed then looks like a taylor expansion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With uh this prefecture alpha n and this alpha n is basically all the terms that you get from the taylor expansion and it’s given by an integral over these transition rates that’s called also the jump moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the moments of these transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the probability the probability distributions uh distribution is described by moments like the variance the mean higher order moments yeah and these prefectures here and the taylor expansions are the moments of the transition rates they’re also called jump moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s that’s how they’re defined and this is still doesn’t look very convenient it’s called the chromosome expansion but it doesn’t look very convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you do know is you arbitrarily stop this expansion in the second order yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you then get if you get it do it to the second order is uh we’ve got p of x t that’s equal to minus del x alpha one of x p of x t plus second moment second order one half del x squared alpha two of x p of x t yeah and that’s becomes a little box no because it has a name after the name is called the plunk equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As i said we arbitrarily truncated the taylor expansion after the second order and i mean by arbitrary i mean that it’s really arbitrary if you if you normally truncate something you would say okay that’s good enough it gets better if i take into account higher order higher orders for the equation that’s typically that’s not not always the case you know it’s an arbitrary cutoff after the second order but it’s uh has some intuitive meaning you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This term here if you look at this what what does this what does this first order derivative here what does it do think about it what this derivative do it shifts the probability distribution to the left and right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is positive here and then it will go to the right and if it’s negative it will go to the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it does here it doesn’t change the shape of the distribution but it changes approximation but it moves it around yeah and because it does that it’s called the drift term and this drift term as i said has the property that the time evolution of this average of x is just given by this drift term alpha one yum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Average okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first term describes the deterministic evolution of the probability distribution the second term can also be complicated but it has this second order derivative here yeah and second order derivatives what do they do they minimize fluctuations in your probability distribution they smooth everything out suppose that you have initially a fixed a small localized distribution like a delta distribution or.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where your system is at a very confined state then the second term will make this distribution wider and wider typically yeah and because it does that and because it looks like it this is to record the diffusion term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focal plug equation we have a very nice separation like in the launch of the equation between the drift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital deterministic components and between the effects that reshape and broaden the probability distribution because of noise and that’s described by this diffusion term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focal plane equation as you can see in the assumptions that we made here we basically assumed that this delta x.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uh the jumps that i make in this system if i go from x to x prime or the other way around that these are small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implicitly that means that we make very strong constraints on our transition rates or how the system can evolve and essentially essentially we assume that it is that it involves in the continuous way and this is what you get if your system is very large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you could say uh if you say you have like oil in water then you have a lot of molecules and if you add another water molecule into your glass yeah then the actual concentrations will not change that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So these are one of the some of the scenarios where you’re actually then it’s fine to look at the fact focus equation and i’ll show you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specific scenario of uh this focal plunk equation and how it can feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We come to the example part of the lecture and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re roughly one hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll show you some examples and um those of you who are phd students who know all of this can drop out if you want yeah or just read it online and for the others i’ll go through the examples uh quickly and then you can on the website you can then download the slides go to the calculations&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/mpipks-non-equilibrium-physics-transcript-02-stochastic-process</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/mpipks-non-equilibrium-physics-transcript-02-stochastic-process</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>马普所·非平衡态系统中的集体过程·笔记 | 01.简介：朗之万方程和响应函数、热力学平衡和细致平衡条件</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;来来回回地协调了好几次时间之后，我们最终确定每周三下午进行一次讨论。刚刚过去的这一周讨论了第一讲，时长超过了一个小时。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在讨论会之前，我的主要精力放在了仅有的几张有公式的幻灯片上，结果这一部分完全没有出现在讨论当中。讨论的主要内容是组里本科生艾萨提出的问题：“细致平衡条件 (detailed balance) 和平衡 (equilibrium) 的关系是什么”。这个问题其实挺有质量的，而且我们确实也没有给出一个令人满意的回答。我觉得要想说清楚这个问题，其实需要的是逻辑学和科学哲学，我现在在这方面的水平还不够，这篇文章姑且尝试解释一下。不过不谈数学的原因恐怕不是在这方面没有疑问，毕竟一不用做作业，二没有考试，完全出于兴趣的情况下，直面数学是需要热情和勇气的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;朗之万方程和响应函数&quot;&gt;朗之万方程和响应函数&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;朗之万方程&quot;&gt;朗之万方程&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;讲义第12页到15页，讲解了热力学平衡条件下的朗之万方程。所谓热力学平衡条件，真正用到的性质就只有能量均分定理。朗之万方程听起来高大上，实际上只不过是对牛顿第二定律进行了一下改写，明确指明了这个系统受到两种力的作用，下面的公式里，等号右边第一项是正比于速度的衰减项，防止方程的解在无限远处发散（”所以你承认你们科学家是在瞎编咯？”），另外一项是一个关于时间的随机函数，用来刻画不确定性的涨落。&lt;/p&gt;

\[m \frac{d^2x(t)}{dt^2} = -\lambda \frac{dx(t)}{dt} + \xi(t)\]

&lt;p&gt;朗之万是和爱因斯坦以及居里夫人（咳咳）同时代的人，依然可以用牛顿时代的东西青史标名，可见物理学果然还是内卷不足，广阔天地，大有可为。（逃）&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;粒子的位置是粒子之前受力作用的积累响应函数是卷积的核&quot;&gt;粒子的位置是粒子之前受力作用的积累：响应函数是卷积的核&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所谓牛顿第二定律，对于高中生来说是公式，对于大学生来说是方程，（“公式和方程有啥区别？”），对于刚上大学的高中毕业生来说是噩梦—— \(F=ma\)  是方程？这玩意需要解？这玩意也能解？这玩意怎么解？三个字母倒真不算方程，但是物理受到的力往往取决于其所在的位置 \(x(t)\) ，所以F其实是 \(F(x(t))\) ；\(a\)  是加速度，位置的二阶导数，也就是 \(d^2x(t)/dt^2\) ，这里的未知量是 \(x(t)\)，这是一个微分方程，常微分方程往往是本科阶段要上一个学期的课程。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;响应函数用的是另一套思路，先不从微分方程的角度入手，直接来猜猜解应该长什么样子。此刻的位置与一段时间以前的受力以及当时的那个力对此刻残留的影响有关，这个“一段时间”究竟是多长时间呢？不知道，索性考虑所有时间长度，把这些影响全都加起来。学过微积分应该知道，对无限个无穷小量求和，再取个极限，这就是积分（“快把那个要先证明积分存在并收敛的数学家嘴堵上”），写作：&lt;/p&gt;

\[x(t) = \int_{-\infty}^{t}h(t-\tau)\xi(\tau)d\tau\]

&lt;p&gt;熟悉数学的朋友知道，等号右边的积分叫做卷积。一般卷积的定义里形式稍有不同，积分上下限分别是正负无穷，这对物理学家不是问题，只要令  \(\tau &amp;gt; t\)  的时候  \(h(t-\tau) = 0\)   就行了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一方面，卷积既是一种定义在两个函数（\(\xi\) 和 \(h\)）之间的运算，可以简写作&lt;/p&gt;

\[x = h * \xi\]

&lt;p&gt;另一方面，也可以看作是对 \(\xi\) 的变换 (transform)，  \(h(t-\tau)\) 是这个变换的核 (kernal)，也就是讲义中所讲的 response function。当一个具体问题确定的时候，方程的解就和响应函数一一对应。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在方程实际被求解之前，响应函数和待求解的函数一样，是一个未知量。因为牛顿第二定律是一个二阶微分方程，要想求解，所以很自然的思路就是将方程两边同时做傅里叶变换，将导数转化为含有 iw 的代数方程，然后再将解做傅里叶逆变换。因为两个函数的卷积的傅里叶变换，等于两个函数各自的傅里叶变换的乘积，所以在傅里叶倒空间里，方程的解、响应函数、随机涨落三项是很简单的乘积形式。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;关于朗之万方程的解讲义中不清楚的地方&quot;&gt;关于朗之万方程的解，讲义中不清楚的地方&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第14页右侧蓝字似乎是 “spectral density”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第15页 \(\tilde{C}(\omega)\) 似乎是 \(\left&amp;lt;\tilde v(\omega)^2\right&amp;gt;\)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;平衡-equilibrium-和细致平衡-detailed-balance&quot;&gt;平衡 (equilibrium) 和细致平衡 (detailed balance)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;先贴几个相关的链接：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thermal_equilibrium&quot;&gt;维基百科：thermal equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thermodynamic_equilibrium&quot;&gt;维基百科：thermaldynamic equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detailed_balance&quot;&gt;维基百科：detailed balance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://physicallensonthecell.org/chemical-physics/equilibrium-means-detailed-balance&quot;&gt;Physical Lens on the Cell: Equilibrium Means Detailed Balance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;目前直接在谷歌搜索 “equilibrium” 并进入维基百科的话会发现找不到和物理有关的词条，因为 “mechanical equilibrium”, “thermal equilibrium”, “thermaldynamic equilibrium” 是几个独立的词条，而且都没有链接到 “equilibrium” 的消歧义页面上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所谓 “mechanical equilibrium”，就是受力平衡，分为三种：稳定平衡、不稳定平衡、随遇平衡。实际上就是牛顿第二定律作为一个动力学方程，其中的稳定、不稳定和中性三种驻点 (fixed point)，和这一讲的关系不大。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;热平衡简单。&lt;strong&gt;两个&lt;/strong&gt; 系统处于热平衡，那么两个系统的温度相同。&lt;strong&gt;一个&lt;/strong&gt; 系统处于热平衡，指的是这个系统温度时间上恒定，空间上均一。虽然这样说有点鸡贼了，盗用了读者在日常生活中对“温度”的理解。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;热力学平衡的条件严格一些，不止热平衡，还要达到机械平衡，化学平衡，所有宏观上的热力学物理量（温度、质心坐标、粒子数……）都没有变化。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;据此，大概可以归纳物理中一般性的“平衡”概念：某种物理性质在一个系统中的平衡，指的是这种物理量在系统内时间上的恒定，空间上的均匀；在多个系统之间的平衡，指的是这一物理量在这些系统之间没有流动。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;其实上面这一段的草稿里，“指的是这个系统温度时间上恒定，空间上均一”后面想当然地来了一句“也就是任意两个子系统之间相互平衡”。当你听到了两个系统之间的平衡之后，再想到一个系统可以划分为多个子系统，思维的惯性就会用类比的方法来如此定义一个系统的平衡。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但是其实仔细一想，“时间上恒定，空间上均一”并不一定要求任意两个子系统之间相互平衡，但是任意两个子系统互相平衡是一个很有趣的状态，我们给他起名叫“细致平衡”。当任意两个子系统互相平衡的时候，可以确定地达到时间上恒定空间上均一的结果。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;所以这是我对艾萨问题的回答：&lt;/strong&gt;细致平衡条件是平衡的充分不必要条件。之所以常有这样的疑惑，是因为平衡的定义不能递归，一个系统的平衡和多个系统之间的平衡定义不同。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上面最后一个链接可以说是直接回答了艾萨的问题，但是这个页面的主标题是 “Equilibrium Means Detailed Balance”, 字面意思是“平衡意味着细致平衡”，也就是说平衡是细致平衡的充分条件，和我前面说的相反。但是文章的内容实际并没有讨论究竟是谁蕴含谁，所以姑且可以无视这个标题。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;细致平衡条件在维基百科词条的正文中称作 “principle of detailed balance”，也就是说这是一个“原理”，和“定律”(law) 一样，这是科学 &lt;strong&gt;理论&lt;/strong&gt; 这一逻辑体系的公理，是没办法在理论内部通过逻辑推导来证明或者证伪的。我们之所以采用这些原理（也就是认为他们是真命题），是因为现有的 &lt;strong&gt;实验&lt;/strong&gt; 全都没有证明这些原理不正确。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;多说两句，科学虽然存在理论，但归根结底是一种经验科学，必须落地于实验和观测。（这里的“经验”对应于“理性”，是有严格定义的哲学概念，不是我们日常用语中所说的那个经验。）而观测和实验总有认知的的边界，边界以外的事情科学家做不了保证，所以实验总没有办法一劳永逸地说某某是对的，只能说某某还没错。只要证而不伪，科学就说这是一个真命题。科学与非科学的界限，根据波普尔的科学哲学理论，就在于&lt;a href=&quot;https://program-think.blogspot.com/2015/10/What-is-Science.html&quot;&gt;可证伪性&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;另外讨论课里完全没有涉及的一点是，这里的“子系统”必须依然是“宏观的”(macroscopic)，各个子系统只能是小一号的总系统，（用软件工程的话说，定义的接口是一样的），不涉及组成这个系统的微观机制（不能是另一类对象）。比如说一盒理想气体，子系统只能是给盒子里加上隔板后的几小盒理想气体，不能精确到具体的气体原子分子，否则此时连机械平衡都满足不了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这和经典力学里的“宏观无穷小”这一扭曲的概念有异曲同工之妙。归根结底，是因为宏观的科学理论建立得不够早，已经用上了微积分；但又太早，没考虑也不知道更低层次的物理规律。经典力学的更低层次已经形成了量子力学，而热力学的底层统计物理就只能和热力学挤在一起，和理论力学、电动力学、量子力学并列为四大力学，逃不出“N 大某某有 (N+1) 个”的魔咒。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/mipks-non-equilibrium-physics-note-01-introduction</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/mipks-non-equilibrium-physics-note-01-introduction</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>马普所·非平衡态系统中的集体过程·语音转录 | 01. Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;《非平衡态系统中的集体过程 (Collective processes in non-equilibrium systems)》是位于德累斯顿的马克思普朗克复杂物理研究所 (Max Planck Institute for the Physics of Complex Systems) Steffen Rulands 研究员的一门课程。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;课程主页&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pks.mpg.de/statistical-physics-of-living-systems/teaching/collective-processes-in-non-equilibrium-systems/&quot;&gt;链接在此&lt;/a&gt;，网页上有课程的课件，录像发布于 YouTube。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;YouTube 把视频中讲者说的话从语音转化成了文字，我把这些转录复制了下来，进行了简单的断句，并且推测了各段文字对应的课件的内容。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;这是&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lm4jR_k08EM&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot;&gt;第一讲&lt;/a&gt;，内容分为两部分，首先是简单介绍了课程，然后讲解了朗之万方程在平衡态前提下解的性质，以此引出研究非平衡态物理的必要性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-1&quot;&gt;Slide 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to do everything over wi-fi..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome everyone to this term’s lecture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is stefan. I’m a group leader here at the pks at the max planck institute for physics of complex systems, and we have quite a few people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally our lectures have like only 10 people most, and that’s because we’re a research institute yeah and that means we normally don’t do a lot of teaching because we don’t have to, but sometimes we do it once in a year HAHAHAjust for for fun and this is this lecture is the same spirit that we’re drawing out something new that we’re giving a lecture for fun and see what comes out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start this is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already had some technical issues well that would probably be a common uh theme for the rest of this lecture. And some of these issues will be sorted out by NAME yeah who’s here in the room with me and who’s the only person in the room at the moment well because we’re as everybody else we’re back in lockdown and YI TANG is probably at the bottom of the list you can write to him in the chat in case you have any questions or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like him if you can’t hear me then just send a message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So i’ll share my screen you should still be able to see me yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-2&quot;&gt;Slide 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the lecture and today i would just like to give you an overview of what all of this is about you know and to give you some information that allow you to decide whether you want to follow the lecture for the rest of the term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess there are quite a lot of people that are dialing in from abroad you know or from not even india i’ve seen and um.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to let you know where you are at the moment you’re joining a lecturer that is taking place in the max planck institute mpi pks in briston and this max planck institute is focused on theoretical physics that’s an explanation for the physics of complex systems we’re doing directive biophysics we’re doing condensed metaphysics and also atomic physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the three branches of this lecture and um we’re covering all of these these aspects from the perspective of the rate of physics as you can see it is quite nice here although placing a little bit in the corner of germany also sometimes a little bit difficult to get here to get out which turned out to be a benefit in the times of corona virus. This is the institute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-non-equilibrium-systems&quot;&gt;1. Non-Equilibrium Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-3&quot;&gt;Slide 3:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to start this lecture to give you an idea what we’ll be doing this term i’m just showing you some of kinds of systems that will be covered at least in spirit in this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you see here are three examples of systems that all share some striking spatial temporal structures and all of these structures arise because there are some microscopic or some interactions on the small scale on larger scale and macroscopic scales then these interactions lead to some interesting phenomena to the emergence of order and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the left hand side you see a swarm of fish i look at the name but what they do these fish do they rotate in these torus structures not to distract predators you know that’s what they do and these interactions are thus just a result of alignment interactions yeah. All right i hope you can see that. The microscopic scale each fish aligns its velocity to some some fish in the neighborhood and in the microscopic cell and then getting swarmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second picture it’s another example of collective processes that’s the emergence of traffic jumps. You have the traffic the phenomenon that traffic jams arise spontaneously and these spontaneous traffic jams are a collective phenomenon that arise from interactions between individual drivers and in particular how they break in response to changing the velocities of other drivers. On the microscopic scale we here have changes in velocity yeah and out of this you get a macroscopic phenomenon and longest case due to these interactions that is trafficked [Music] that’s taking a place on much smaller scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what you see here is uh what’s going on inside the cancer cell and what you see is the cytoskeleton yeah we see here is lung fibers macroscopic or mesoscopic fibers of molecular assemblies and these fibers are also built by genetic processes of proteins attaching and detaching from these fibers. Here in this case you have molecular interactions that give rise to uh the two to through macroscopic structures that in the end then control the shape of cells and also partially their movement yeah the cycle skeleton i apologize for this for the for my handwriting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;I’m waiting actually for a very nice 12 inch ipad but it was not delivered yet so. I’m in the unfortunate situation that i’m writing just on a 12 inch 10 inch ipad yeah which is of course much smaller yeah and that’s why my handwriting is a little bit uh not that good. But that will improve over the course of this lecture on the once the delivery comes.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the three examples and in all of these examples physics has played an important role in understanding these collective processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-4-breaking-of-microscopic-symmetries&quot;&gt;Slide 4: Breaking of microscopic symmetries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we need actually physicists what do we need to study to understand collective behavior in such systems? right maybe even even simpler example is water and ice water is made of water molecules and we need we know exactly what water molecules do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can probably solve the friday schrodinger equation for a single motor molecule at least numerically but once you put these water molecules together and you know the temperature you get ice crystals and if you zoom on even further you get these complex structures that are snowflakes and these patterns that you see here in these ice crystals are in your way in the hamiltonian that describes the quantum dynamics of a water molecule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What that means is that for example the water molecule is of Schroedinger equation is a rotationally invariant translationally invariant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can rotate the trigonometric dimension and then the trigonometry equation you still get the same behavior these macroscopic structures here these ice crystals they don’t obey the same symmetries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have symmetry breaking as we push these water molecules together and let them interact and the symmetry breaking is often called emergence and give rise to the complexity that we see in nature and biology and also in social systems yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The macroscopic behavior of such systems does not necessarily obey the laws that govern the microscopic say on the the microscopic structures don’t follow the same symmetries as the microscopic descriptions such as the trigonal equation yeah if they did everything was easy and nature would be pretty boring as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that these macroscopic structures follow different laws than government on the microscopic scale and we need sophisticated tools from statistical physics and non-equilibrium statistical physics to connect these different levels these different scales to connect the microscopic interactions to macroscopic phenomena yeah that’s what a large part of which is what statistical physics is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-5-big-data-in-public-helth&quot;&gt;Slide 5: Big data in public helth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time in recent years we probably became aware of that this whole thing that’s called big data yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re able to study complex systems with unprecedented detail empirically where we can take measurements in quantities that were impossible a few years ago and one examples are of is of course social systems that underlie of course for example the spreading of epidemics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for example if you look at what these people do that do covet modeling also they take it you can’t trace the traces and you have these abstracts like traits your movement that creates your traits your interactions and you have all of these data this data on the level of a very high microscopic resolution of single individuals of course you test people you trace them they know who is infected who is not affected to some degree and then you also know who is interacting with whom else yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know something about the social interactions things about this i think think about social networks like facebook huge data available made available that describe social systems on this on the scale of individual interactions yeah and of course in other elections in the united states is of course also true for elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years it has become increasingly clear that people hire data big data companies that digest all of this data about voter preferences and so on to make predictions about or the best counties to approach and so on and that’s certainly true for the us but also for the uk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-6-big-date-in-bioilogy-genomics&quot;&gt;Slide 6: Big date in bioilogy (genomics)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of where such high dimensional and huge data sets emerged is biology.In biology we have seen technological breakthroughs in recent years. They also allow us to study biological system systems in unprecedented microscopic detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several technologies that imaging involved but one of these breakthroughs was in genomics that’s also something something we’re working on in the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These breakthroughs in genomics allow us to measure the state of individual cells the molecular states of individual cells with unprecedented detail that was not possible before. As you see here on this slide you see an example of such an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s hd was conducted by collaborators in cambridge and here. You see information. This is just a point of this information that is gathered together in these experiments and what you see here are measurements on individual positions of the dna.That’s what’s on the x-axis. The x-axis here gives you the position on the dna like the genome and for each of these positions for each of these molecules that the dna is made of you can measure whether there is a modification of this molecule or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what you see in the bottom half of this plot and in this top half of the plot you can see you can measure something about how the dna is folded in this region of the genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you download such an experiment that comes with like a terabyte of data as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a huge amount of data and you cannot only do that for a single cell but you can do that for many different cells at the same time and that’s what’s on the y-axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on the y-axis are different cells at the same of taking from an embryo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-7-function-relies-on-collective-properties&quot;&gt;Slide 7: Function relies on collective properties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we in principle can measure the molecular state of cells of all cells from the early mouse embryo yeah and that’s in physics not something that we do very efficiently but we don’t start an experiment and measure every single thing in a magnet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t uh measure every single velocity of uh particles of every single particle in a gas. That’s not typically how we think of to do macroscopic measurements in biology and social sciences we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approach these systems on a microscopic scale with almost arbitrary details and that of course gives rise to questions about how do we connect these two developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we take such large data sets and translate them to understanding of collective processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would you actually want to do something like this if you describe something if you can measure everything on the microscopic level? why do you actually want to understand something why i actually interested in these collective processes and the reason is actually very well depicted in this car. Here if i give you a list of the microscopic parts the car is made of you would have a hard time understanding how this car works or how an engine works and of course how this works how this car works it’s not a property of all of these individual screws and tires and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On it’s it’s a property of how all of these things work together as the function of this car depends on how they work together and how they work together is not immediately you cannot immediately deduce from listing all of the cars the paths are measuring all of the parts the car is made of and the same also comes through of course in biology but biological function does not rely on individual molecules in the cell they are biological function relies on how this molecule works together and then have some microscopic or mesoscopic consequences yeah and this is exactly the question that we want to address in this lecture here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-8-focus-of-this-lecture&quot;&gt;Slide 8: Focus of this lecture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;what are the actually the tools that we need to understand that we need to know in order to unders identify and to understand collective processes collective behavior in systems that are out of thermal equilibrium and traditionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like me and probably many of you we’ve been educated in equilibrium systems we had statistical physics lectures and statistical mechanics maybe this is some mechanics too you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That are that deal with some very specialized cases in um the also the internal equilibrium yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gas that is somehow isolated or that is in contact with some heat bath. So these are very special cases and we then try to use our understanding that we gained in our statistical mechanics lectures on criticality transitions and so on and we try to transfer that to one equilibrium system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole rest of the systems that are out there yeah and that’s what we do and it actually works quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re making some of course we have developed tools also non-equilibrium physics but our intuition was typically trained in equilibrium systems and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The the goal of this lecture is actually to identify what is actually the intuition that you need one of the tools that you need in order to derive these collective properties of systems that consist of many interacting two-way particles and also on the one hand we have these high-dimensional data sets like the ones that i showed you and the question is how do we treat these data sets in order to derive theories in order to build hypotheses [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we actually treat this data set how do we derive the hypothesis how do we understand the structure in such highly dimensional reach data sets and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is that we will need some tools from data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-9-overview&quot;&gt;Slide 9: Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to deal with data sets that in the case that i’ve shown you have millions of dimensions yeah the reverse direction is actually how do i understand order from microscopic theories yeah and these tools that we need for that come from non-equilibrium statistical physics that then allow us to make predictions from theories that allow us to infer how do we once we have the theory once we have a microscopic description of biological or social systems how do we derive collective processes from this how do we derive collective degrees of freedom from this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the two ways that we will deal with in this lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is this is how it will work in practice yeah and we will start with a basic introduction into stochastic processes and also a field theory. It would be good if you could give me some feedback. I don’t know how many people are we know oh 63. So it would be good if you give some feedback what’s actually your background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the website and i think on twitter i don’t know direct website i said that uh what what you need is a basic understanding of not basic understanding but you need to have a statistical physics lecture yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t be shocked to uh shouldn’t be the first standard that you hear what it faced about a phase transition it should be the first time to hear about entropy also yeah and say it’s a statistical physics lecture and building on top of that then we introduced some things that we can’t rely on having been told the statistical physics lectures which are sarcastic processes and non-equilibrium theories of past integral representations of these stochastic processes and then we go on and ask how do microscopic directions lead to macroscopic order actually i have a little torch here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do microsoft the macros microscopic interactions give rise to macroscopic or and of course there’s no general theory for this in non-equilibrium systems we don’t know how this works in general but we can use some constructive examples that would like in statistical physics and equilibrium statistical physics would be the izing model that’s a very very powerful example for second-order phase transitions and we’ll deal here in the second part with some very powerful examples of monochemical systems of how order arises in non-aggregate systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we’ll go on to study transitions between these ordered states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-equilibrium phase transitions we’ll introduce regularization group theory and talk about non-equilibrium criticality and look at some very specific phase transitions so-called absorbing state-based conditions that are very relevant for epidemics and actually i have a few examples from epidemics in this lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we ask the reverse question the reverse arrow and how do we actually identify such collective order in data sets that come with terabytes of size and 10 million dimensions how do i actually identify how can i actually efficiently on a computer deal with these kind of data sets and how can i use statistical tools for machine learning to break these to identify structure in such data i also will have then some applications from real research and finally as a bonus we’ll have we’ll discuss we’ll ask the reverse question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not how microscopic order gives rise to microscopic interactions give rise to macroscopic order but we’ll ask how does macroscopic order shape microscopic states that’s the reverse question it’s a very new question in the in the field but that has some very interesting application for example for neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the structure of the of the code and i’m very actually very happy also to adapt to your needs if time permits yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just send an email if you have any questions or anything else yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-10-prerequisite-and-literature&quot;&gt;Slide 10: Prerequisite and Literature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have prerequisites statistical physics yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We make use of functional analysis yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s typically taught also uh before statistical physics i think but that’s a helpful tool but you need but if you don’t have that it’s also enough to reduce that quickly with a lecture the field theory is also helpful i don’t give a rigorous introduction to field theory in general but i’ll introduce a few theories that we need here for this specific course but if you know already some 3d theory you’ll see that things are actually quite similar to using quantum field theory sort of quantum systems for example yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually a problem yeah because there’s no book that tells you exactly the story that we want to address in this course and i’ll give you some literature for each of these sections that we’re going to deal with some generally quite good books especially for the first part of the lecture are the ones by elkland and science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A condensed metal field theory that that covers this fluency we aspect one equilibrium theory aspect and the same book by coming up on non-equipment theory basic tells the same perspective the same perspective from the more quantum point of view they’re just dealing with one part of the lecture and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;This lecture is generally as you know taking place tuesdays at 4 40 pm cet and will last typically for one and a half hour but i’m a little bit hesitant to talk with one of my power on zoom because i know how tiring this can be and. What i’ll do i’ll have the content of one in our blackboard lecture but usually because of this ipad and.On we’ll cover that that stuff in a quicker time because i have don’t have that much writing and but calculations are always write them on the ipad. I’m not going too fast through them um. That’s the lecture and then there’s a website also i can’t remember the exact. That’s the that’s the group website and if you look for teaching you’ll see a link to this course and i’ll upload if technology permits. I’ll upload first slides of pdfs of what is written in the lecture and also try to upload the video videos of the of the lecture i can’t promise it for this one because um i have to just hope that it works and but i’ll also post links to videos at least starting on the next lecture where i figured out how all of these things work here.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-11&quot;&gt;Slide 11&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to start today to start today for the rest of the lecture i’ll just [Music] give you a brief um reminder of actually how we can see that a system is out of equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of systems that we’re dealing with in this lecture and the simplest answers you can uh take that you can hear is that any system is out of equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to have very very extremely special cases where systems are actually internal equilibrium and anything you see in biology for sure in those social systems is out of the equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is actually already um part of this way that everything is non-equilibrium system yeah but given that we learn statistical physics typically in equilibrium systems just let me make sure that we all are on the same page to understand what it means to be not internal equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we be out of thermal equilibrium equilibrium and why is it important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing is what you can do is if you look at these plots of these pictures that i showed you um at the beginning of the lecture the fish spawn and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On there’s one thing that’s already striking fear if you have listen to the to the statistical physics lectures is that something’s wrong with the second law of thermodynamics apparently right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the second law of thermodynamics basically in a very rudimentary way states that entropy increases in systems that are isolated yeah and they determine that they approach some equilibrium stable maximum entropy and that often is obviously not the case for the systems that i showed you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re not in this state that you would assume to be in terms of equilibrium and because they’re very dynamic and highly structured yeah and the reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you how can you break some say the second law i hope that enough like hardcore statistical physics i have always have the quotes of course the second floor is correct that’s the one way you can avoid this is that a system is just not isolated and one of the conditions for the second law yeah the first thing is the system is isolated yeah it’s isolated but it doesn’t haven’t reached equilibrium yet but it will do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some rate of time yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples are for example chemical reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also on the right hand side here you see this you see these this this this dish here and there’s some chemical in this dish and what you see what you see of this was a video still have to figure out how to show videos and this note notepad application here yeah but these are waves more that progress here and you have rotating spiral waves here electrons are target waves that toggle with as you see that they do some kind of positive circular wave patterns here and this is obviously more than equilibrium but this system alternating equilibrium homogeneous state here such as the fuel that it’s based on is all consumed that’s called the bzec reaction and of course another example of a system that’s probably isolated is the universe yeah and the universe is very far away from equilibrium as you can just see by looking at the sky and but it will approach some equilibrium state of mass and entropy in very long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of a system that is approaching equilibrium but it’s not an equilibrium yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other kind of systems the other way of how you can avoid the second law is if the system is just not isolated but it’s open and what that means is it’s coupled to some kind of boundaries and physics we typically call that baths yeah that exchange for example entropy energy or particles with this system and these these are the kind of systems these open systems that we are dealing with in this lecture yeah and probably in your statistical physics lectures um you have dealt with some open systems that were nevertheless in equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why you have the all these different ensembles in statistical physics because we have these open systems that can exchange particles or energy with their environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system that is open is not can still be an equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we mainly what how can we make a system stay out of equilibrium an open system out of equilibrium yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-12-what-keeps-a-system-out-of-equilibrium&quot;&gt;Slide 12: What keeps a system out of equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can consider a very simple example here and this very simple example is just a particle this red particle here and this red particle just follows some kind of trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is given by some kind of hamiltonian some hamiltonian dynamics yeah and then this particle here will do some ballistic motion but at some point it will collide with other particles in the same system and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two effects that such collisions can have yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one is that on a microscopic level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That which is the amount then you will see that the movement of this particle is slowed down yeah and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These collisions on on a on a long time scale give rise or hinder the motion of the particle that’s typically what’s called friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s another thing that these collisions do namely they lead to abrupt changes in the velocity and in the direction of your particle yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act these repeated collisions act like a fluctuating force that all the time pushes this particle in a different direction and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can write down the equation of differential equation that describes the motion of such a particle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s just a generalization of newton’s law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That you would mean that mass times acceleration the velocity time derivative of velocity is equal to minus the mass that’s the friction times v times the velocity plus whatever external force you apply to the system and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comes this fluctuating force psi that i mentioned previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such as such an equation describes the particles the dynamics of these systems it looks like newton’s equation but we have this weird force on the right hand side on the right hand side that is described to you in more detail in a few minutes yeah and this equation has a name it’s just probably most of you know that is to launch on a equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this launcher equation has a few troops yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only this randomly fluctuating force but we also have this gamma here that’s just the dissipative friction it’s called dissipative friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It describes how some of all of these collisions decrease the velocity of this particle and then we have some extrinsic macroscopic force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You tilt the system left or right and then you apply the force to the particle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have this floating randomly fluctuating force that’s the last component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-13-properties-of-the-fluctuating-force&quot;&gt;Slide 13: properties of the fluctuating force&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is this force and what is this about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this force is a random variable yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you’ve heard the statistics lectures it’s the random variable it takes the random value at each instant of time and it’s not just any random value but we know from the central limit theorem that if you sum up a lot of these forces you know then the net result in some time interval will follow a normal distribution or a gaussian distribution like this as we say in physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central central limit theory tells us that we’re probably doing quite well if we approximate sine of t with a gaussian or a normal distribution as a goal is a commotion random variable yeah that’s already nice because the fortune distributions are always quite nice to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what we also know is that his force is not always pushing in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the average of this force is zero it has vanishing mean you know soy average of soil of t is zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it has a non-zero mean you could just absorb it in some other part of the equation yeah and then we have to say something how this force is random force how strong it is and how it is evolves over time yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this we describe in terms of the correlation autocorrelation of this force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course we make these assumptions because everything is very messy that this force is uncorrelated in time yeah that means that the correlation of psi of t with psi at some other time t prime [Music] is some value a well that’s the strength of the noise times the delta function t minus t prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also only correlated to itself it doesn’t have any memory why this A is just the strength of the noise or fluctuations of this fluctuating force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-14-in-equilibrium-fluctuations-and-dissipation-are-strictly-coupled&quot;&gt;Slide 14: in equilibrium, fluctuations and dissipation are strictly coupled&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will show you that if this particle if this system is an equilibrium then this strength of this force here is already determined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we already know the strength of this curve with this force and particularly i will show you that this force is actually determined by the friction the force and the friction are not independent quantities and comes a little experiment because i have to do the first calculation of this lecture um if this experiment fails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because uh for whatever reason it’s also important because it’s not we’re still much in the sort of state theory real theory part of this lecture that was next week but i’m just just giving you something some intuition about what it means to be in equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at this equation again and the first thing we do is we do a Fourier transformation yeah we say for a transformation we say that this fourier transform of the velocity of this particles as a function of some omega frequency omega is just the definition of the fourier transform e to the i w t v of t yeah and if you plug this in and just look at the equation again here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we’ll get some some i the i from the exponential comes i’m sorry is the pointer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the i from the exponential comes down at the omega as well because we have the time derivative and and the rest is basically just a linear term yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we then get if we fully transform is that we have um minus on omega from the exponential here the fourier transform is equal to minus m gamma fourier transform of the velocity plus the fourier transform of the mods yeah so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an algebraic equation and we can solve this formally we can solve this formally and say that v tilde is equal to 1 over minus i omega plus m gamma times sine tilde.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can just write that down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So because we can’t do anything with that i can write it down and it’s prefecture here is typically called the response function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our omega and this response function gives how the velocity reacts to a fluctuating force yeah so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We look at the fourier transform of the velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at the fourier transform of fluctuations of these correlations in fluctuations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at the fourier transform of this quantity here psi of t psi or zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For t prime t prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we plug that again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just do the same trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sine of omega sine of omega prime is equal to the integral over dt e to the i wt and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The correlator psi of t times t prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to make use of the four properties of the fourier transform especially the fourier transform of delta functions just one and that we see in the furious phase this correlated with correlations and the fluctuating force are just equal to 8 and this is sometimes called spectral density that’s not important excuse me um the equation on the the very first equation it would be like exponential minus i omega t right yes yes and then there will be the on the second line there will be minus i omega m v yes that’s correct and there will be the m factor will be like in common in the denominator on the let’s hear third exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s correct that’s correct actually actually that’s exactly how i have the notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May i have a question regarding the previous slide yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s it’s really maybe it’s just a very nice question but um the fact that we allow our zeity to follow the central limit theorem and hence follow a gaussian distribution it just reminds me of the maxwell distribution of velocities which is one of the crux of thermodynamics and thermal equilibrium conditions why do we allow zai to follow gaussian distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the the the sign is uh the strength or it is a force that’s acting at each time point yeah on on the velocity it’s not the velocity itself there’s a force that’s acting on the [Music] force that’s acting on the velocity and it’s just random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have yeah you suppose you you have a time interval delta t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time interval you have 10 million forces acting on your particles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That you that means that your velocity is equal to your old velocity and then along some over these 10 million identically distributed random variables yes yeah it’s just a very basic statistical thing that this is a gaussian distribution in many cases it’s not gaussian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many examples where it’s not caution but that’s typically cases where things get very very messy yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s well beyond the scope of the lecture but there’s still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your your opponent the master distribution is actually very good because we still have to if the v in equilibrium still has to fulfill the maxwell’s distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You still you still have a constraint that the constraint is not whether the constraint is not in the gaussian distribution but it’s in the a the pre-factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s that’s where the equilibrium condition goes into and i’ll show you actually i’ll show you that in the next step here yeah um so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can we have the correlations and noise and we can just calculate the correlations and velocity velocities as well v of omega v of omega prime that’s equal to something like one over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do the same thing as both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two times this pre-factor i omega and plus gamma m squared and then on the right hand side we have the force yeah and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we can do from that is that we can calculate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we know that the right hand side here remembers the pointer this one here is just equal to a yeah and we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back to real space to real time perform this integral and by performing this intro we have to do some contour integral yeah it’s not extremely important how this how this integral is exactly works it’s a contour integral because you have here something a prefactor that has some rules and then you can use a residual theory well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do here a contour integral no and then we get a over 2 m squared gamma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another situation until.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have assumed that the system is an equilibrium but if we assume that is that it is an equilibrium then the equi-partition theory you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We partition theorem as a state that basically the energy of the system is distributed equally across all degrees of freedom and this theorem tells us that the kinetic energy gets fraction of or is equal to kbt over 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-15&quot;&gt;Slide 15&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that’s. where i put the condition of thermal equilibrium and what we get from that is just what you see here in this box here this a the strength of this fluctuating force is equal to a term that contains the friction coefficient at the temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By setting this one parameter in the equation the gamma or gamma times m by setting this in the equation by fixing this you already know the strength of the fluctuating force yeah and this is just a manifestation it’s called einstein relation and it’s a manifestation of the very important fluctuation dissipation theory in statistical physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fluctuation dissipation theorem tells you that the strength of the fluctuating force in your system of the strength of fluctuations is given by the strength of friction and in general terms you can write this as i write down here on the left hand side you have the strength of fluctuation of the strength of correlations in v they are already exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This this [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This these correlations are something like sorry something like sine omega sine omega prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the general fluctuation dissipation the strength of this fluctuating force the strength of fluctuations in my velocities due to this force is given by this response function the imaginary part of the response function and this response function is essentially in this case determined by the friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to read this fluctuation dissipation theorem is that the intake of energy that this particle gets through this fluctuating force needs to be exactly balanced by the loss of energy due to friction yeah and this is true if we are internal equilibrium and that also means that we can use this fluctuation dissipation theorem to decide when we’re not in equilibrium [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example there’s a theorem that says that if we calculate a quantity called j which is just just the total deviation in this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-16-what-happens-if-we-couple-the-particle-to-an-additional-energy-reservior&quot;&gt;Slide 16: what happens if we couple the particle to an additional energy reservior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this does not hold true if this is not equal on both sides yeah then the amount of disagreement tells you something about how far you are from equilibrium yeah c prime let’s see the derivative of omega minus 2 kbt imaginary part of the response function r of omega if we calculate that then we know this quantity j and this quantity j is just the amount of dissipated heat yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are out of equilibrium if you they violate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You say the second law you have to cap from the compensate for that in your environment and that means that the media need to export heat to environment and this is quantified in this equation and it tells you how far away you are from terminal equilibrium that’s ethereum by [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-17&quot;&gt;Slide 17&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s continue with our part with our particle here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we make this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we drive this system out of equilibrium and turns out it’s actually pretty simple yeah and this there’s actually a very specific biological example for that and these are bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the bacteria have so-called flagella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are these little hairs here and the tails and these flagella can rotate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when these flagellar rotate then this material can move holistically that will let us rotate through a medium through through space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy from the environment for example glucose for example glucose yeah then that metabolize this energy and convert it to kinematic one part of it they converted to kinematic energy to kinetic energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can move in one certain direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can write down the larger equation for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the same as before and v dot equals minus m gamma v plus epsilon [Music] k v.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This epsilon kb comes from here let’s just simply use this energy epsilon here that you metabolize and you put it into kinetic energy as this one here yeah then you get a force that corresponds to this one here epsilon kv force plus of course your collisions with your neighbors yeah the point is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we have a second friction terminal that has an opposite sign but in principle we can set the second friction terminal that’s the total total dissipation term bisection called participation actually amount of terms that are proportional to b yeah and we cannot do the same calculation as before but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pre-factors of what we call previously the gamma the pre-factors of the spectrum can take any value that we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s up to the bacteria to digest material to digest nutrients and convert into into [Music] into kinematic energies there are of course some constraints in terms of chemistry of metabolism and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On it’s not a certain maximum amount that you can achieve but in principle you’re free to choose your epsilon and your k in whichever way you want you can make that time dependent or whatever yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that by this choice here by converting chemical energy to kinematic energy this bacterium breaks the fluctuation dissipation theory and this is because dissipation is independent of fluctuations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-factor of these fluctuations here is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely independent of the pre-factor of these dissipative terms and we can get whatever we want and break the fluctuation dissipation theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This material is called an active particle or active brownian motion is out of terminal [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the general pattern behind this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We break detail the rate the fluctuation dissipation theorem and then we are out of terminal equilibrium but how can we do that in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s a general topic behind that and this general theme is that you have an isolated system you couple it to some boundary conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically we’ll say boundary conditions in physics we say both yeah and in some cases this bath if it’s nicely behaved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s also an equilibrium then this whole system will also take an equilibrium state but if you couple it to multiple balls for example a hot and cold one HAHAHAthat then your system is out of equilibrium if these bulbs are not compatible with each other for example here in this case of active browning motions that we just discussed we have different bars that couple to the fluctuation and dissipation parts in the fluctuation dissipation no [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particle takes up chemical energy and converts it into this this movement yeah by a reaction that typically involves the conversion of atp to adp yeah that’s how living systems uh use energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same yeah and because this particle moves around it needs to increase because this particle is let’s say it needs to increase heat in the surrounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means it’s coupled to a heat path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It dissipates heat to a heat pump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slide-18&quot;&gt;Slide 18&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are many other examples in physics that you can see one famous example is turbulence turbulence uh probably if you set saw one of these airplane videos with the turbulence behind the airplanes is a big problem you have an intuition what turbulence is and in turbulence kinetic energy of this velocity fluctuation uh cascades from some large spatial scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For probably the scale of the airplane turbine also all the way down to some small scales where it’s then dissipated yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case you have different bars at different scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a heat path on a large scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where you input energy and then you dissipate this energy on smaller small enough scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s here small scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also a heat bars because it takes up energy yeah [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were in live lecture a live lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would ask you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For suggestions for other assistants but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only italians here and i would always have to ask and but.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people who come from biological physics this approach with the baths with the coupling the system to bounce is not very natural in our case we typically define a non-equilibrium nature of the systems of non-aggregate systems by probability fluxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microscopic levels are the same but this idea with the bath is also quite general and actually comes from another lecture that i gave last year with a colleague from condensed measure physics and in condensed metaphysics and quantum systems the idea of a bath is much more natural and then it’s a very nice exercise to translate our favorite non-equilibrium systems in social sciences and biological physics and just sort of say to say and ask actually what are the the two incompatible paths that drive these systems out of equilibrium and in some systems like epidemics and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These answers is pretty pretty difficult and but maybe we can do that at the end of this this term yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this i i’m finishing the lecture for today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q--a-session&quot;&gt;Q &amp;amp; A session&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excuse me stefan yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work in biological physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I i do study gene transcriptional regulatory networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The for example you have a transcription factor that regulates a target gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transcription factor may may be regarded as the bath for the regulated gene is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you keep the long sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transcription factor is that that can be regarded as a bath for the regulated gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing one thing you have to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not entirely sure but one thing you have to think about is whether your system consumes energy in any case yeah um because at some point you have to use atp yeah if you at some point you have to use atp and then you have the chemical bar somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this chemical part is hidden somewhere in some in another place but my guess is that if it’s a non-equilibrium process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a normal enzyme kinetics is not it’s an equilibrium yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to do something like if you modify chromatin the transcription make a transcription factor modify chromatin and sometimes you lock that in with epigenetic marks and these epigenetic marks then all the such that the irreversible step of they they are the step that require energy yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say it depends on the transcription factor like everything in biology that’s it’s it’s probably very complicated thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot for your question um are there any other questions yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering an example of a heavy iron collision in a particle accelerator um.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The the experiments there they start with the particles colliding at extremely high energies and then there is a phase that they thermalize and then the particles also convert into other particles and that is the sort of the general way how the system evolves but that is more or less will study through equilibrium and statistical methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could you you know with reference to today’s terms that you introduced in the lecture regarding like the fluctuation strength of fluctuation and other factors could you explain with examples on that with that particular experiments experiment probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think i think probably until.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already the coolest thing about this lecture is that we seem to have an extremely diverse audience yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re getting some questions here from particle accelerators i think in this case the equilibrium is actually fine yeah because you don’t inject the energy you have you inject the energy once into the system and then you let it evolve yes yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know like in this particle you’re not this you’re not basically continuously injecting more energy while the condition takes place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You inject it once like in the human universe you check it once at the beginning and then you let it evolve and at some point you’ll reach some equilibrium state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not being an expert in elementary particle physics i would actually naively think that equilibrium is actually quite fine but isn’t it exactly like the example we did before of the universe which is considered as a non-equilibrium system which is isolated yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this the universe is non-equilibrium of course yes but it’s an isolated system i guess yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an isolated system and because it’s an isolated system it needs to obey the second law of thermodynamics that means you get all the consequences like the entropy increases and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that the universe at some very distant future will be in a state of maximum entropy that’s what people refer to when they say like entropy death of the universe or whatever yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will reach some state of maximum entropy and um let me think exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um yeah i think i think in terms of the the particle collisions you have to um you have to yes and you have to i think you have to think about time scales here yeah um with respect to the times i think if you take the limit of t tending to infinity that really depends on the scalar t to infinity for t to infinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for t to infinity you know that your system will end up in equilibrium if it’s isolated yeah because you ejected the energy at some point yeah and then you and then you isolate it and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that at some point it will be in equilibrium the question is how long does it take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s a question that i cannot answer without elementary particle physics knowledge for example in physics we have examples where systems you take them out of equilibrium and then you see what happens and they will never reach equilibrium actually yeah because that’s called aging yeah they very very slowly have a very slow dynamics and then it goes back yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This these are systems where you wouldn’t say that you would make like equilibrium approximations HAHAHAif you have a system that exponentially relaxes back to a steady state to the equilibrium that you you you perturb it and then you see what happens but it immediately goes back to the equilibrium state yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What i’m saying is that that with these time scales that the question is how long does it actually take to go to equilibrium and that’s a that’s probably a question that is very specific for these kind of systems that set equilibrium is much easier than non-equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could just be that people just make the the approximation f equilibrium approximation without well actually saying that it’s actually more than equilibrium for example in physics and statistical physics we have own saga theory that describes systems that are just a little bit out of equilibrium and what this theory actually says is that if you go out of equilibrium then you have still have the same kind of fluctuations as actually in equilibrium itself yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example where you when you say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My system is not an equilibrium but i treat it something like an equilibrium system and thank you for the answer and another question is are we allowed to chop our system which we know is going to eventually end up in equilibrium and we chop the system at a certain point of time where it still hasn’t reached equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It becomes a valid case study for non-equilibrium statistical physics we deliberately chop it yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So fHAHAHAit’s one thing i have to say that that all of these systems are valid case studies for non-equilibrium physics we just.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a whole field of this first case of system that these glasses all these glasses glassy dynamics spinning glasses and.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On neural networks these things they they fall in this neural network is not a very good example but all these glasses are certainly non-equilibrium systems because they for a very long time stayed out of equilibrium but at some point it will be an equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m here talking about systems that contacts we also say sometimes active systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That constantly take up energy from the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about biological systems are they constantly for a cell to survive you always have to convert atp to adp you always have to take up chemical energy always otherwise the biological systems can’t keep up the complex structures that are going in the process that are going on inside cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you stop this process the cell is death that yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So i’m here talking about systems that constantly take up this energy yeah and at any instant in time yeah and [Music].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding your question once you’re out of equilibrium you’re basically it’s very hard to make general statements it’s not like an equilibrium where we have our partition function and then we have phase transitions and renormalization and criticality and universality these kind of things are much more difficult and non-equilibrium systems yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer your question they think that probably the the the answer depends on how what exact system you chop up otherwise it’s quite likely that there’s no general answer to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you thank you for your question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there any other questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you if there are no other questions if you have any feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just send me an email this week i’ll try to implement it and also if you have any thing that’s useful for you that you want to learn in this lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just also send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t promise that i’ll i’ll be able to implement that because it’s already quite tight um but this letter is sort of also a little bit experiment yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are actually the tools that we need to get some understanding of these non-equilibrium systems yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are actually the the the fundamental concepts that we need to understand yeah and the answer to this might be quite different for each of us and it would be quite keen to learn about what’s your background and what are you what are you hoping to get from your neck from this lecture yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just send me an email and um with that see you see you all next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are no questions then i’ll close the lecture and see you all next week same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/mpipks-non-equilibrium-physics-transcript-01-Introduction</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/mpipks-non-equilibrium-physics-transcript-01-Introduction</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>【2020Matters年度问卷】Normality Matters</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Matters 是一个博客平台，在前几年区块链和去中心化思想还很热的时候上线，底层所有的博文会上传到 IPFS 区中心化平台，账号可以绑定一种叫做 LikeCoin 的数字货币，用来赞赏作者。2019年11月28日，我在 Matters 上传了自己翻译的 Paul Graham 的《How to Disagree》，算是正式加入了 Matters 社区。在那之前，我虽然建立了自己的博客(https:mountaye.github.io/blog)和公众号，但是一直没有规律性的更新。可以说，过去一年所有的不务正业，都可以以 Matters 为线索串联起来。我一向不擅长赶 deadline，所以压根没做周年纪念的打算。结果发现 Matters 官方有红包，没办法，只能为五斗米折腰了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020年只剩下最後十天分享一件在年初想不到今年會發生的一件事這件事對你的生活帶來什麼樣的改變&quot;&gt;2020年只剩下最後十天，分享一件在年初想不到今年會發生的一件事？這件事對你的生活帶來什麼樣的改變？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;美国股市对新冠大流行的 V 形走势。标普500指数从2月中下旬开始跳水，用了一个月的时间跌去三分之一，然后开始了大牛市一样的攀升，八月底重回疫情前的高点。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018年1月份，我的开户申请被 Robinhood 批准，从此成为了美国股市里茁壮成长的一棵小韭菜。结果就在开户的那周，美股就开始下跌。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;那时候人们开始说，十年一个小周期，到了崩盘的时候了，结果涨涨跌跌地拉锯了几个月，创出新高；十月再次开始大跌，也就是段子里讲的10天4次熔断那次，那时候人们又说，十年一个周期，出来混，到了还的时候了，结果这回更快，只用了四个月就收复之前的高点；如今，已经没有人再说十年啊周期啊什么的了，YouTube 上的雷公视频的标题，也从“市场进入高危期”变成了“急跌就是买点”。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“热闹是他们的，我什么也没有。”不只是没有的问题，我还在这期间花了很多仓位做空，兜兜转转，不断跌破止损线，累积下来，损失了大约一个月的工资。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;要说这对我生活的改变，可能是……让我最近两个月没有文章更新？不断的亏损之后痛定思痛，觉得问题主要出现在记账方面。之前和股票相关的账目都是用一个 MS Excel 电子表格记录，虽然自认为还算准确完备，但是一方面只包含了自己的已经发生的交易信息，另一方面数字也不如图形直观，很难给将来的交易决策提供帮助。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因而，我决定把记账这件事转移到 Jupyter Notebook 上，完成 Excel 表的功能之外，还可以把自己的买卖价位和股价走势画在同一张图上，把自己的仓位和市场的交易量画在同一张图上，辅助决策。同时还可以练习 python 数据可视化的能力、&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ipywidgets&lt;/code&gt; 组件写 UI 的能力，一举多得。所以最近一段时间的业余都在忙这件事，博客也就暂时停更了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020年什麼事情讓你獲得最深的意義感&quot;&gt;2020年，什麼事情讓你獲得最深的意義感？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;定期用无人机空拍校园。这件事刚刚付诸实施，每月选一天，沿着相同的线路拍一段延时摄影。预计明年的这个时候才会有结果，所以严格来讲不算是2020年的事情。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;定期是一种获得意义感的很有效的方式。高中的时候，我们学校的几个老师和同学们办了一份报纸，每周三晚自习前免费分发几十份给每个班。高三一年的每一期报纸我都集齐了，每个周三，我都在学校食堂暴风吸入晚饭，然后跑回教室等发报纸的同学。一年下来，攒下来的报纸对折起来，几乎和课桌的抽屉一样厚。人非星辰大海，没办法占据无限的时间，但是周期性的事件序列，具有时间上的平移对称性，周期函数的自变量是可以趋向无穷的，给人一种对于永恒的近似和安慰。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;摄影也是。像我这样的人，可能没办法给学校捐个楼，把自己的名字刻在楼基的石碑上，但是在这里学习和工作的经历，还有校园的景色，“耳得之而为声，目遇之而成色，是造物者之无尽藏也，而吾与子之所共适。”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;全球疫情依然嚴峻請記錄一件你認為值得銘記的疫情事件&quot;&gt;全球疫情依然嚴峻，請記錄一件你認為值得銘記的疫情事件。&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11月初的年度进展报告。从去年夏天的资格考试通过之后，每年11月初，我们都要向导师委员会汇报自己这一年的工作进展。今年的报告结束之后，第二天和老板单独 Zoom 的时候他表扬了我，说今年的进展依然不错，委员会的成员都印象深刻。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我现在的工作主要包括两部分，一部分是用我们老板做博士后的时候用的成像方法，去观察和他当时的工作稍有不同的细胞，属于“承上”；另一部分是“启下”，因为旧的方法在性能上不足以研究更复杂的系统，所以需要开发新的图像处理技术。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;美国的疫情从2月份开始，那时候我刚刚拍了一些用于开发新技术所需要的参考图像，所以封城令最严格的几周有可以在家工作的素材。夏天限制条件放松之后，我又回到学校用旧方法拍了很多照片，这些照片在进行数据分析之前，需要在计算机集群上进行做“去卷积”计算，比较耗时，但同样可以在家做。所以今年的工作节奏，实际上并没受到病毒的太多干扰。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但是我也知道，这种印象深刻的另一面是，在今年以前的我的工作效率，也没有比有疫情的时候有多大的优势。之前工作也有很多时候摸鱼，我也不会加班，业余时间也在折腾自己的爱好，简直约等于不务正业的同时顺便读了个博。疫情把“我们所浪费的时间本质上都是自愿选择的”这一点放大了，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020出行受限如何改變了你與他人世界的關係有沒有什麼人事是疫情過去你一定要去見做的&quot;&gt;2020出行受限，如何改變了你與他人/世界的關係？有沒有什麼人/事，是疫情過去你一定要去見/做的？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;恍然发现原来自由出行也可能变成一种奢侈。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;疫情之后，我想我会成为一名 B 站的 up 主，像 Youtube 上的 Thomas Heaton 一样，到处走走拍拍，用拍视频这件事来鞭策自己，注视自己可能来之不易的日常，并珍视对这些日常的记忆。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;說一件你在2020年遭遇的難以解決的矛盾這裡的矛盾是指你感受到自己的信念與行為產生了衝突&quot;&gt;說一件你在2020年遭遇的、難以解決的矛盾，這裡的矛盾是指：你感受到自己的信念與行為產生了衝突。&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;自视清高和渴望吸引眼球的矛盾。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;明知道在任何平台写东西，用真名挂各种头衔会多很多流量，但还是用化名，努力避免 ad hominem 谬误；明知道在 Matters 写东西，用简体字没有流量，不谈政治没有流量，不做赞赏公民没有流量，也还是坚持下来了；明知道在微信写东西，膜蛤可能会死，借古讽今可能会死，点了关注的读者可能再也没看过我的更新（微信信息流的锅），但还是在危险的边缘疯狂试探。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;分享一個你忽然理解了我所反對的立場的時刻&quot;&gt;分享一個你「忽然理解了我所反對的立場」的時刻。&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;没有，而且我觉得也没办法有，“忽然”、“理解”和“立场”本来就不应该出现在同一个句子里，你要是真的能理解，那早干什么去了？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;公共讨论中的绝大多数问题并不是因为拒绝对话，而是急于对话，把根本不成立的对话强行推进下去，结果就是鸡同鸭讲，各自在自己的信息茧房里赢得一片掌声，然后一个共识，各自表述，直到其中一方得意忘形进入了对方的同温层，再开启一轮循环。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;相比一年前你與身體的關係發生了什麼變化你有更喜歡現在自己的身體嗎&quot;&gt;相比一年前，你與身體的關係發生了什麼變化？你有更喜歡現在自己的身體嗎？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;老了，虽然我才 20 多岁。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;天冷的时候跑步，膝盖就会疼。刚来学校的时候，参加系里的老教授们每周踢足球的活动，还笑他们冬天休赛期太长，现在只能摸着自己的膝盖感叹自己还是 too young too simple, sometimes naive. 小时候练羽毛球，从场中央来到网前需要两步，退到底线需要三步；现在一步半就到了，但是再也不敢跑折返了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当然，作为一个减肥成功的胖子，我经历过更难受的肥胖状态，我对今天的身体已经足够满意，不敢再奢求更多。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;經過2020年你內心是否有找到一個關於自己不可停止之事嗎&quot;&gt;經過2020年，你內心是否有找到一個關於自己，不可停止之事嗎？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;认识自己——不断修正对自己的认识，并且证明这种认识。（你现在还认识“认识”这两个字吗XD）&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;請與我們分享你在-2020年最常聽的一首歌最愛的一本書或者印象最深刻的一部電影&quot;&gt;請與我們分享你在 2020年最常聽的一首歌、最愛的一本書或者印象最深刻的一部電影&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;戈德门特《代数学教程》。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;最後能否請你用一張照片代表你的-2020-年&quot;&gt;最後，能否請你用一張照片代表你的 2020 年。&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2021-01-09-matters-rainbow.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;填空2020normality-matters&quot;&gt;填空：2020，&lt;u&gt;normality&lt;/u&gt; matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;好像真的赶不上 deadline 了，后面几个问题越来越敷衍……应该不影响拿红包吧（小声）&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/matters-yearly</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/matters-yearly</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>.md | 扫盲Barrier，用笔记本键鼠无线控制台式机</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;为啥要用-barrier&quot;&gt;为啥要用 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Barrier&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;圣诞节前的周五，我们系在线上办了一个聚会。和学姐闲聊的时候，听说他们高年级的几个朋友每周一起联机玩《文明6》，于是一番理(卑)直(躬)气(屈)壮(膝)的要(恳)求之后，成功加入了组织，等到了 steam 的圣诞特惠（没错我一直没买 new frontier pass，我是云玩家），准备以物理学工作者的严谨态度，研究《文明6》诱导的基于回合的反常时间平移对称现象。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-livingroom.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我现在公寓房间的结构如图所示，前任房客走的急，把她的几乎全部家具低价甩卖给我了，四舍五入相当于白捡了一台大电视。电视用 HDMI 线连接电脑，当作第二显示器使用。躺在沙发上，看着大屏幕，玩着文明6，&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bilibili.com/video/BV1g441187zq&quot;&gt;运用自如&lt;/a&gt;的话说——“那岂不是非！常！爽！”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所以说，我的要求是：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;在笔记本和台式机处于同一 Wifi 的情况下——&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;笔记本电脑和台式机之间不需要任何数据线连接&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;使用 Linux 笔记本上的触控板、鼠标和键盘&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;控制 Windows 台式机&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;正常运行和操作《文明6》，不会因为延迟卡顿被人喷（卡顿是不存在的，只可能掉线lol）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一番搜索之后，锁定了 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Barrier&lt;/code&gt; 这款软件。它可以设定一个 server 和多个 client，用 server 的输入设备控制各个 client。切换方法也很方便，只要提前约定好各个设备的“相对位置”，当 server 的鼠标光标跨过 server 屏幕的边角处，就开始控制对应方向上的设备。（具体可以查看下一节。）&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;之所以选择它，主要原因如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/debauchee/barrier&quot;&gt;开源软件&lt;/a&gt;，堂堂正正地不用花钱。（我知道开源软件≠免费软件，但是……）&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;目前依然有人维护，GutHub 上还有上百个 open issues，当然 closed issues 更多，有问题可以查，提问也有人回答。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;跨平台，Windows 和 Linux 都能用。主流 Linux 发行版都可以在仓库里找到，也可以通过 snap 安装。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;如何配置-barrier&quot;&gt;如何配置 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Barrier&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;下载和安装&quot;&gt;下载和安装：&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因为我的发行版是 Fedora，在笔记本的 terminal 上任选一句运行：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;sudo &lt;/span&gt;dnf &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;barrier
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;sudo &lt;/span&gt;snap &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;barrier
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;台式机是 Windows 10，在GitHub 项目（&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/debauchee/barrier/releases&quot;&gt;链接在此&lt;/a&gt;）里找到最新一期的发布版本，找到 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt; 结尾的文件（可以用浏览器的页内搜索），下载，双击下载后的文件安装。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;配置-server-笔记本电脑&quot;&gt;配置 server （笔记本电脑）：&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;首先要确定 linux 的桌面环境是基于 xorg 的，当前版本的 GNOME 默认使用的是 Wayland，所以需要 log out 之后重新选择带有 xorg 字样的环境，如下图：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-gnome-environments-new.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;安装完成之后，在 app 界面（&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Win&lt;/code&gt;+&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;）应该可以找到 barrier 的图标，单击即运行。一般来说之后会有相当长一段时间电脑没有反应，这个时候 &lt;strong&gt;千万不要重复点击图标&lt;/strong&gt;，会导致无法连接。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-barrier_linux_desktop.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;之后会看到软件的主界面，选中图中所示的选项：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-barrier_linux_start.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;然后单击 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;configure server&lt;/code&gt; 按钮，进入下图的界面，拖动右上角的电脑屏幕图标，拖到中间屏幕周围的任意一格。我选了右边一格，因为这样在笔记本上向右滑鼠标会进入台式机的显示器，从显示器右边框向右会进入电视，一路反过来就回到了笔记本屏幕，操作比较自然。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-barrier_linux_config.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;双击图标后会弹出一个新窗口，在最上面的 “screen name” 栏填入 client 上显示的本机名称，现在我们还没有配置 client，所以需要等到配置完之后回来填写。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-barrier_linux_naming.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;注意主窗口的左下角，如果不是 “barrier is running” 的话，需要点击右下方的 reload，还是不行的话就要准备 debug 了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;配置-client-台式机&quot;&gt;配置 client （台式机）：&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;安装完成之后，应该能在开始菜单里找到 barrier 的图标，点击运行，应该会看到和笔记本上面差不多的界面。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-barrier_windows_main.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;选择图中的选项，填入笔记本窗口中显示的本机 IP 地址，选中 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;auto config&lt;/code&gt; 选项，然后点击右下方的 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;start&lt;/code&gt;，然后窗口左下角同样应该有 “barrier is running” 字样。点击菜单栏里的  -&amp;gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show log&lt;/code&gt; 打开日志，应该可以看到下图里的 “connected to server” 字样。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-12-22-barrier_windows_log.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;几个雷点&quot;&gt;几个雷点：&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fedora 的显示管理器默认并不使用 xorg，需要专门切换。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linux 上启动较慢，如果不耐烦多点了几次，可能会重复打开多个实例，造成端口被占用，无法使用。
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;诊断方法：打开 log 界面，会发现 “ERROR: cannot listen for clients: cannot bind address: Address already in use”  字样。&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;解决方法：杀掉多余的进程，不会杀的话就重启电脑吧。&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;server 和各个 client 对是否使用 SSL 的选择必须是一致的。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;官方没有按步骤来的配置说明，这么多雷点，我居然看到好几篇博客都在夸 barrier 的界面多么通俗易懂，简直了。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;barrier-之外的其他方案&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Barrier&lt;/code&gt; 之外的其他方案&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;synergy&lt;/code&gt;：成熟的商业软件，好像要花钱。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Microsoft Garage Mouse without Borders&lt;/code&gt;：要求所有设备都使用 Windows 系统，不适用于我的笔记本电脑&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;usbip&lt;/code&gt;：来自 farseerfc 大神的&lt;a href=&quot;https://farseerfc.me/zhs/usbip-forward-raspberrypi.html&quot;&gt;这篇博文&lt;/a&gt;，原文说“设置好的话，就像是一台 PC 多了几个位于树莓派上的 USB 端口，插上树莓派的 USB 设备统统作为 PC 的设备”。
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Barrier&lt;/code&gt; 相比，配置的步骤更繁琐；&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;好像一次只能控制一台设备（不太懂，如果转发给多个设备的话可能会一起执行相同的操作？）；&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;好像也不适用于非 USB 接口的设备，比如笔记本的原生键盘和触屏笔；&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;一旦运行起来，server 的鼠标就不再能够控制自己，所以原文使用了几乎注定吃灰的树莓派，相当于给键盘加了个广播天线。&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- 用的是一款叫作 [Gather](https://gather.town/) 的 web 应用，就像 90 年代的 RPG 游戏一样，参加者每人指挥一个像素很糊的人物，在一个像素很糊的房间里走来走去，不同之处在于当角色相互靠近到一定距离之内的时候，可以像 Zoom 一样视频连线。 --&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/barrier-forward-keyboard-mouse-to-another-computer</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/barrier-forward-keyboard-mouse-to-another-computer</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>.doc | 经验介绍会</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;本文为虚构。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;大三的时候，我们高中的班主任熊师傅找到我，问我想不想回学校，给学弟学妹们介绍介绍经验，加加油，鼓鼓劲。我当时直接傻了，没开玩笑吧？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;高三那年的清明假期，我们年级别出心裁，趁着已经上了大学的学长们放假回家，而我们还在学校自习的机会，把他们请回来，开个主题班会，和大家近距离地见见面，给我们介绍经验，加油鼓劲。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我们年级当然有这样的底气。我们这样的十八线小城，一中那时北大清华还不是每年都有的，三年前的这批老师，一年教出了两个北大，老熊当时的班级，是全年级一本率最高的。我们这一年又是第一次推行北大校长实名推荐制度，校长为了给北大一个好印象，选中了本来上北大就没什么问题的年级第二，所以一场高考大捷已经十拿九稳。只不过年级第一有点不高兴，为学校实现了数学奥赛零的突破之后，赌气一般地直接和上交签约了。显然，这只是学校从一个胜利走向另一个胜利过程中的一点小小杂音，不足为虑。在这次经验介绍会之前，年级主任即将在高考结束之后升任副校长的传言，就已经在晚饭时段的闲谈中流传开了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;听说这个的时候，我的心里很不以为意。不以为意很正常，十八线小城里的优等生，高考之前瞧得起谁呢？但还不那么简单，主要是因为同样的戏码，初中的时候已经看过一遍了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;初中不幸，误入一个作业极多的学校。多到什么程度呢？我们入学的时候接近70个人，毕业之前转学走了12个。除了1个去东北的高考移民，剩下11个人都是转到了本区的其他中学——为啥？累的啊！什么996，什么福报？Too young too simple! 互联网大佬们啊还是要再学习一个，学不下去怎么办，打鸡血啊！开学一个月左右的时候，班主任请来了刚刚以全市第一名考上一中的学姐，还有另外两个学长，回来给我们介绍经验，加油鼓劲。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;温柔美丽的学姐和学长们如约而至。有一说一，这场经验介绍本身还是很成功的。一上来，学姐抚今追昔，指着教室中间一位漂亮可爱，马尾长辫黑又亮……咳咳，不好意思油腻了，指着一位女生说，当年她就坐在同样的位置。轻轻一番话语，就拉近了我们和学姐之间的距离。然后学习经验整理得井井有条，用排比的方式，介绍了课前认真预习、课上认真听讲、课后认真复习三大法宝。学姐还有一个姐姐，也曾是全市第一上一中，今年刚刚被北大录取，只要你足够努力，北大也在等着你，耶！作业多怎么办？这就是请多位学长学姐来的好处了，曾任语文课代表的学长站出来非常有斗争经验地说，你们课代表可以给老师求求情啊，老师又不是那么不近人情的人啊（班主任是语文老师）……总之，学长学姐学习成绩优异，人物形象丰富，总有一款你的菜。放学回家的时候，我骑车到路口，学姐站在不远处等公交车，牛仔裤，白衬衫，晚夏的风向后吹起了她的长发，哇，美！&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;然后呢，作业还是他妈的多，撑不下去的同学开始转学。爸妈实在看不下去了，开始帮我写作业，期末最累的时候给我请病假让我在家补觉。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;班会开始之前大家的笔都没有停。老熊走进教室，看了一会自习，看了下门外，对我们说：“来，差不多了吧，让我们有请——”平时吱吱呀呀的塑钢门被很有礼貌地推开了，一位穿衬衫的干净男生走了进来。老熊作完介绍，学长的 PPT 也准备好了。一上来，学长抚今追昔，指着教室中间一位玉树临风的男生说，当年他就坐在同样的位置。然后……然后不是学习经验三大法宝了，但是究竟说了什么我也不记得了，记忆就是这么奇怪，久远如初中的事情还历历在目，后来的事情却朦胧不清。只记得他问了几个问题，我们给出了让聊天无法进行下去的尴尬回答。然后学长开始介绍山大的校园，讲到了自己正在领导的学生会部门，幻灯片上是学生会的照片，学长的旁边站着一位美丽大方的学姐。“这个嘛，工作上的同事。”学长解释时露出了微笑，男生们在意味不明的“哦”之后在微笑和大笑之间猥琐地笑，此刻写下这些文字的我自嘲地笑。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;几个月后的高考成了整个年级的滑铁卢。我的全校排名仅次于某次超水平发挥的期中考试，但总分依然比平时低了二三十分；北大校荐的同学加了六十分后依然不够被录取；全市第一名是一位补习学校的复读生。当然了，喜报还是发在了市里的报纸上，毕竟一本过线人数再创新高。只不过新任副校长人选是兄弟年级的主任，上大学后看学弟们转发的 QQ 空间里的动态，英姿勃发的校长一夜之间头发全白。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;写到这里的我实在是写不下去了，写这些干什么呢？是想幸灾乐祸吗？不应该，这样一场溃败，每个人都是受害者，我也并不置身事外。是想咀嚼一番回忆的苦涩吗？不存在，高考的成绩不是十分理想，客观上减轻了我在大学时竞争的激烈程度，让我得以进入第一志愿专业里一个不错的班级，交换生出国，奖学金，我的四年大学生活没有什么遗憾。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;退言思之，可能我想说的是，滑铁卢并不是拿破仑一个人的滑铁卢，真正承担伤亡的，是一个个籍籍无名的普通士兵。拿破仑尚且还可以在偏远孤僻的小岛上了此残生，内伊元帅甚至可以慷概骄傲地命令行刑队向自己开枪，如果“无内鬼，来点苏联笑话”，现代传媒甚至可以让人不知道拿破仑的失败，可那些败兵呢？他们只能包扎好伤口，掩埋好战友，然后解甲归田，或者继续前行。是的，可以解甲归田了。上了大学，及格万岁，只要你不违纪，不跳楼，课随便翘，游戏随便打，有了外卖更是可以屁股长在椅子上，眼睛长在屏幕上。那谁还努力啊，又有什么事情值得努力呢？我也不知道，但是晚上自己在教室里刷题的时候，为了公派背单词的时候，听身旁的同学骄傲地谈论自己全国闻名的高中母校的时候，我的眼前总是浮现出校长满头白发的那张照片。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;只是这些话，无论如何不可能出现在经验介绍会上。那我能说什么呢？不如抚今追昔，指一位教室中间的男生或女生，说当年自己就坐在同样的位置吧。&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/doc-share-experience</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/doc-share-experience</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>.xls | 聊聊买车这两年多</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;2018 年初，趁着寒假的功夫考了驾照，趁热打铁买了车，是一辆二手的丰田花冠。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最近有个朋友要买车了，知道我有车，所以来打听一下；碰巧我也临时起意想要换车，之前对买车和养车的花费，虽然一直在记账，但是脑子里是一团糨糊，需要理一理。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;结果呢，在这篇文章动笔之前，朋友就已经秀出新车的照片了；算完买车的帐之后，我也暂时决定不换车了。所以这篇文章，权当是周更凑数吧。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;先来算帐&quot;&gt;先来算帐&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因为隐私的关系，所有价格都是约数，这样可以减小一点点&lt;a href=&quot;https://program-think.blogspot.com/2017/12/howto-cover-your-tracks-10.html&quot;&gt;信息量&lt;/a&gt;（虽然没什么用就是了）.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;与车有关的花费可以按照频率来归类：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;一次性的：
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;汽车本身，给车行的：约 $13,000&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;消费税：约 $1,300&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;每年一次：
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;财产税：从第二年开始，年末交，至今只有一次，$300&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;半年一次：
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;保险：大约是个等差数列，$2100 开始，之后每次下降 $200&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;保养：没有特殊项目的话，$20 - $30&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;每月一次：
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;加油：车用的少，平均每月一箱油。最贵的时候每次 $30，最便宜的时候（现在）每次 $20&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;不定期的：
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;为了考驾照租了一辆车：$10&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;换驾照、车牌：每次 $20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;换过一次轮胎：$700&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;换过一次刹车片：$500&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;洗车工具、清洗剂：$50&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;停车：在芝加哥两天停掉了接近 $150 :-( 其余至今累计不到 $100，包括在学校停车&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;再谈感受&quot;&gt;再谈感受&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;价格比想象中贵不少&quot;&gt;价格比想象中贵不少&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;说实话，重新看到帐单的时候我有点不敢相信，虽然来这里的第一天就知道美国的东西标价和税是分开算的，但是我印象里一万三是税后价格。当初买车的预算只有一万元，结果不够，幸好当时爸妈在国内已经起床了，在签合同的当时紧急给我汇了一笔钱。估计是价格太高，花了家里这么多，自己实在惭愧，于是记忆就悄悄地自我修改，帮自己开脱了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一般而言，美国汽车新车的价格是比国内便宜一点，但并没有江湖传言说的差那么多。国内价格按照官价汇率换成美元，和美国税后价格区别就在误差范围以内了。有次我和几个朋友开车路过一家卖野马的车行，大家讨论起来野马新车的价格，我猜的最准。 &lt;del&gt;当然了，官价汇率和实际购买力也有一点不同，微信公众号上不能多说，说多了号就没了。&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;美国买车便宜，主要在于这里的很多人买的都是二手车，一辆车在新车变成二手车的那一刻起贬值是最快的，五年左右的车价就能跌去一半。同时由于市场成熟，因为信息不对称被车商套路的可能性比国内小很多，有更多的人愿意买二手车。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;车险及所谓华人互坑&quot;&gt;车险，及所谓“华人互坑”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;虽然车险价格以一个等差数列稳步下降，但是其实中间换过一家保险公司。头一年半的三次付费是卖车的时候经手的业务员推荐的，看起来像是本地华人经营的一家保险中介，自己没有保险产品，给一些知名度不是那么高的保险公司拉客户。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;卖车的小哥是华人，我当时房东的晚辈亲戚。月均 300+，听起来就好像不怎么靠谱是吧，总感觉应验了豆瓣名言“在海外坑中国人最狠的都是自己人”。第一次交保险的时候简直心头在滴血，就连我这种拖延症晚期患者，在一年半以后也坚决换了某 G 字头知名保险公司。结果回过头来看，价格下降的幅度并没有明显改善，基本是汽车折旧和个人信用记录的正常积累。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当初把保险办好，所有的手续就都齐了，第二天直接拿着车行给的文件就把牌照办好了。我去看车的时候是开着考驾照租的车去的，买完车我再开回来，他帮我把新车开到我的公寓，然后打电话让嫂子开车接自己回家。这样一想，更为自己之前以小人之心度君子之腹而羞愧。这次朋友买车本来是想推荐给他的，结果前不久看朋友圈才知道他已经换了工作，有点可惜。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;我想换车还是算了&quot;&gt;我想换车——还是算了&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;觉得现在反正住得离学校很近，每天去学校也不需要开车，真正用车的机会也就是每周一次踢球、一次去超市，以及不定期的短途瞎逛。这样的用车场景，小车的油耗优势并不明显，出去玩的时候，有时需要走一些石子路，SUV 的通过性有明显的优势。所以有想要换车的打算。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但是，上网看了一些车的报价，标价一万五的都是凤毛麟角，两万以上很普遍。这也正常，毕竟绝大多数的 SUV 和 B 级车同平台，本来就比现在的车大一圈，SUV 本身的功能又有溢价。以我现在的存款，肯定是要先卖旧车再买新车，各种标价之外的成本，再想到各种行政手续也要消耗不少的时间和精力，恐怕只能望而却步。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/xls-two-years-after-buying-car</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/xls-two-years-after-buying-car</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>.py | matplotlib笔记：两种API</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“图”这个字在英语中可以对应好几个词，picture, image, figure, plot… 其中的 plot，意思是展示两组或两组以上的数据之间关系的图像。用时髦一点的话说，就是数据可视化的产物。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所谓&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt;，顾名思义，&lt;del&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mat&lt;/code&gt; 表示山寨 MATLAB&lt;/del&gt;，&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt; 的含义如上所述，&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/code&gt; 表示这是 python 的&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yinwang.org/blog-cn/2017/05/25/dsl&quot;&gt;一个第三方库 (library)，而不是某种领域专用的编程语言 (domain specific languange, DSL)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所谓 API，全称是 application programming interface, 应用程序接口，约等于在你有了自己的数据，想调用 matplotlib 来画图的时候，那些需要写在你自己代码里的语句的语法规则。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因为是代码库，所以在一切开始之前，需要在你的 python 代码开头声明引入&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/code&gt; 可以换成你喜欢并且不和其他代码冲突的名字，但是这三个字母是大家的约定俗成的，网上的绝大多数示例代码都这么写，&lt;del&gt;照抄就完事了。&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matplotlib-的两种-api&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; 的两种 API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; 有两种 API，（其实还有第 3 种 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pylab&lt;/code&gt;，但它没能经得起时间的检验，已经处于官方极不推荐的状态），分别是：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;基于状态的 (state-based)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;面向对象的 (object-oriented)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;两种风格混用的话大概率没法玩得转，会产生各种出人意料的输出结果，新手 debug 的能力又比较差，所以最好先选边站队，有时间再学剩下的一个。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;对于有 MATLAB 基础的朋友，基于状态的 API 语法和 MATLAB 几乎一模一样，几乎可以直接上手，当年 python 算是后起之秀，这一招当初就是为了从 MATLAB 那里吸引用户， &lt;del&gt;相当歹毒。&lt;/del&gt; 这套接口本身也比较简单，适合在调试程序的时候快速看一下结果，检查错误。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;对于一般的初学者，matplotlib 的代码本身就是用面向对象的编程范式写成的，学习这套 API 可以更好的理解代码，知道自己究竟在干什么，顺便还可以熟悉一下面向对象的编程范式。现在学 python 之前就会 MATLAB 的人越来越少，网上 &lt;del&gt;可供复制粘贴&lt;/del&gt; 的示例代码越来越多地使用面向对象的语法，学习面向对象的接口也更加实用。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;两种-api-的相同任务&quot;&gt;两种 API 的相同任务&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-10-04_figure-and-axes.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上图来自网上随便找的一篇论文，可以看到，一般我们会把信息相关的几幅小图放在一起，在文章排版的时候，这张组合在一起的图片算作一个单位。在 matplotlib 里面，这样一个基本单位叫做 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/code&gt;，而每一幅小图叫做 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/code&gt; （变量名常简写作 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/code&gt;）。平时的单图可以看作只有一个 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/code&gt; 的 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/code&gt;，多图的时候往往用一个 tuple &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;axes&lt;/code&gt; 的 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__getitem__()&lt;/code&gt; 方法来控制每个子图。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/photos/2020-10-04_anatomy-of-figure.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上图&lt;a href=&quot;https://matplotlib.org/gallery/showcase/anatomy.html#anatomy-of-a-figure&quot;&gt;来自官网&lt;/a&gt;，图中的蓝字就是 matplotlib 认为的一张只有一个 axis 的 figure 所包含的元素。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;两种 API 要做的事情，就是建立 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/code&gt; 和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/code&gt;，然后提供函数/方法来生成或者改变各个元素。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;基于状态-state-based&quot;&gt;基于状态 (state-based)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所谓基于状态的 API，不太好解释，前面已经说过，在每个函数前面加上 plt，剩下的就和写 MATLAB 几乎完全一样。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;看&lt;a href=&quot;https://matplotlib.org/tutorials/introductory/pyplot.html#sphx-glr-tutorials-introductory-pyplot-py&quot;&gt;官网给出的教程&lt;/a&gt;，可以观察到两个有趣的现象：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;几乎没有赋值运算符 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;几乎所有的 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; 前面都是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;也就是说，与 matplotlib 相关的命令都是函数，而且不需要将返回值赋给任何变量。&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;figure&lt;/code&gt; 和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/code&gt; 的概念被隐藏起来了，&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.figure()&lt;/code&gt; 建立一个 figure；&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.subplot()&lt;/code&gt;建立多个 axes，并且将程序的注意力放到函数参数指定的子图上；紧跟着的设定各种元素的函数都会作用到之前最新一个 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.subplot()&lt;/code&gt; 所指定的子图上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;没有赋值说明函数的返回值并不重要，这些函数都会作用在后台维护的 figure 和 axis 的状态机上面，也就是说这些函数都有副作用，不是纯函数。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;面向对象-object-oriented&quot;&gt;面向对象 (object-oriented)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://matplotlib.org/gallery/showcase/anatomy.html#anatomy-of-a-figure&quot;&gt;作为对比&lt;/a&gt;：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;头几句会有赋值运算符 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;，被赋值的变量名一般就是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/code&gt; 和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/code&gt;。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; 前面都是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/code&gt; 和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/code&gt;，其中 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/code&gt; 居多。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fig&lt;/code&gt; 和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/code&gt; 分别是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matplotlib.figure.Figure&lt;/code&gt; 和 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matplotlib.axes.Axes&lt;/code&gt; 两种对象的实例，画图和调整都是在调用两种对象的方法，主要是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax&lt;/code&gt; 的方法。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;不同之处-cheat-sheet&quot;&gt;不同之处 Cheat Sheet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;绝大多数命令，在两种 API 之下的名字都一样，差别就在于开头究竟是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.&lt;/code&gt; 还是 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax.&lt;/code&gt;，但是少数命令不同，下面做了一个表格，进行一个不完全的列举：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;State-Based&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;任务&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Object-Oriented&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.figure(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;新建 figure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fig = plt.figure(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.subplot(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;新建 axis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax = fig.add_subplot(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;好像没有&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;同时新建 figure 和复数 axes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fig,axes = plt.subplots(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.title(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设置 figrue 标题&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax.set_title(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.xlabel(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设置 x 轴名称&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax.set_xlabel(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.ylabel(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设置 y 轴名称&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax.set_ylabel(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.xlim(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设置 x 轴范围&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax.set_xlim(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;plt.ylim(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设置 y 轴范围&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ax.set_ylim(**args)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;其他不同的命令，以后用到的时候会随手更新。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/py-matplotlib-two-api</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/py-matplotlib-two-api</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>.tex | 整理一些关于实验记录的文章</title>
        <description>&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/careers/2019/09/how-keep-lab-notebook&quot;&gt;微信公众号“BioArt植物”，原作者 Elisabeth Pain ，《实验记录到底怎么记？》&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED344734.pdf&quot;&gt;Howard Kannare, 《Writing the Laboratory Notebook》&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web.mit.edu/me-ugoffice/communication/labnotebooks.pdf&quot;&gt;MIT Department of Mechanical Engineering, 《Instructions for Using Your Laboratory Notebook》&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://xw.qq.com/partner/vivoscreen/20200820A00HZI00?vivoRcdMark=1&quot;&gt;微信公众号“生物学霸”，《颜宁：讲讲如何记实验记录》&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;微信平台不允许添加指向微信之外的超链接，资源的获取方式见正文。作为报复，以上四条资源中有两条最早是在公众号里看到的，但是博文给出的链接都来自微信之外 :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;slender&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;0&quot;&gt;0&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;疫情依旧，摸鱼依旧。摸鱼的方式有很多种，其中比较高级的一种是打着完美主义的旗号，对着一个还没完成，或者根本不存在完成时的东西，疯狂输出时间和精力。琢磨如何完美地进行实验记录就是个挺不错的由头。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;说实话，学界对研究记录的要求实际上并不算严格，这一点在《Writing the Laboratory Notebook》里也有佐证。商业机构研发部门的研究记录会成为将来知识产权争端的主要证据，稍有不慎就是真金白银的经济损失，甚至关乎企业的生死存亡。而学界的工作在“科技”中偏重于”科“（即便是工程学科），在”研发“中偏重于”研“。（四者有什么联系和区别？科学认识世界，技术改造世界，研究把钱变成知识，开发把知识变成钱。）自由比起规范显然更有利于在未知领域的探索。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所以，我们实验室对于实验记录并没有成文的规则，大家自己找本子自己记，格式和内容都跟随自己的喜好来，同实验室的同学也很少交流这个问题，仿佛说了就是承认自己的科研能力有问题。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;越不谈越是心虚，于是在看到了《实验记录到底怎么记？》这篇文章之后，下决心要处理掉这个问题。这篇文章的作者访谈了几个科研人员，然后将他们的对话打碎，分到四个问题之下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;为什么还要花时间精力去做实验记录？&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;用传统纸质的记录本，还是电子版，还是都有？&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;采取什么策略来保证实验记录有条理、完整并且实用？&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;其他……&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;并不推荐这篇文章，原因从这四个问题就能看出来：第一条属于幸存者偏见，一个觉得记录不重要的人压根不会认真记录，从而很难成为访谈对象；第二条属于典型的”有的人……有的人……“英式废话文套路；第三个问题太笼统，本应该细分为更明确的子问题；最后一个“其他”说明作者都不知道该怎么总结这些对话。明明是一篇文章，硬生生写出了微博一般的碎片感。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;于是在网上继续找资源，机缘巧合之下，在一个知乎问题之下看到了一个还不错的答案，里面提到了 Howard Kannare 的《Writing the Laboratory Notebook》这本书。真的是“机缘巧合”，因为现在的我已经找不到原来的那个问题和答案了，哪怕专门为了这篇文章搜索了半天……这说明了网络资源的收藏和管理也是一个技术活（又可以水一篇文章了）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这本书在网上有英文的完整影印版，很容易就能搜到，实在不行的话在微信后台留言”HowardKannare”可以收到下载网址（注意回复的关键词没有空格）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;本书各章的标题如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Reasons for Note keeping - An Overview&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Hardware of Note keeping - Books, Pens, and Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legal and Ethical Aspects - Ownership, Rights, and Obligations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management of Notekeeping - Practices for Issuance, Use, and Storage of Notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organizing and Writing the Notebook - Be Flexible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples of Notebook Entries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patents and Invention Protection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Electronic Notebook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appendix A: Some Suggestions for Teaching Laboratory Notekeeping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appendix B: Photographs from the Historical Laboratory Notebooks of Famous Scientists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;书很长，有 150 多页，这导致内容涉及方方面面，包括了那些我们可能不是那么急需的方面；还有很多我们今天可能并不十分需要的冷知识，比如几十年前美国出产的纸张由于某种工艺导致保存期限比较短等等。好在多数章节最后都有总结，可以帮人省下不少时间。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;另一方面，这本书出版于1985年，那是一个什么年代呢？苹果在前一年才刚刚推出了 Macintosh 电脑，C++ 在当年才刚刚出版。所以对于电子实验记录，书中只在第8章和纸本笔记进行了一个简单的对比，而且有比较明显的时代局限性。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;总之，如果真要读这本书的话，抱着练习英语阅读的目标，要远比学记笔记要少些失望。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;干了半天之后开始怀疑这件事从一开始是否有必要，这可是 PhD 的保留节目了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;尤其是在读过《Writing the Laboratory Notebook》的第5章之后，读到单篇实验报告应该包括 introduction, experimental plan, observations and data, discussion of results 的时候，恍然发现，这不就是本科实验课要交的实验记录的写法吗，之所以没有老师教过我们怎么记实验记录，是不是因为他们觉得这个事情已经教过了？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;既然如此，那么第三份材料就是 MIT 机械系给本科生的实验报告要求，不长，只有 6 页，还包括了超过两页的模板笔记，可以当作《Writing the Laboratory Notebook》关于笔记内容部分的精华集锦来看。微信后台回复 “MITlab” 可以收到 PDF 下载地址。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但这反而说明了，PI们散养研究生，不对实验记录进行更进一步的要求和培训是不对的。因为“实验记录本”≠“实验记录们”，研究生的工作不同于本科实验课，本科生做实验就只有在固定时间和固定时长的实验课上，一切超出规定范围内的动作大概率都是无用功甚至错误，每个实验要做什么，有哪些步骤，会观察到什么现象，都是事先设计好的，实验记录的各个部分会有哪些内容，大体上没跑。研究生的工作则不然，大到整个博士期间的所有工作都可以算作是一个项目（毕竟会写成一篇毕业论文），小到显微镜从开机到观测到关机的几个小时也可以整出一篇报告来，如何划分研究的基本单元？一个人可能同时在做相对独立的多项工作，是连续记录还是分开平行记录？以纸本为主，电子版主要用于备份，还是主要用电子设备，随手记在纸上的拍照作为附件？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;对于这篇文章没有太多可说的，覆盖范围和《实验记录到底怎么记？》类似，感觉就相当于颜宁女士自己一个人对那篇文章中的问题的回答，由于是一个人的回答，所以不会有前一篇文章中不同观点混在一起的分裂感。看过了《Writing the Laboratory Notebook》之后，会发现文中的每一个点都在书中可以找到。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/lab-note</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/lab-note</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>.doc | 人生是马尔科夫过程吗？</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;最近报名了一个写作班，老师留了作业，命题作文——“我想怎样地度过余生”。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我在电脑上敲下了一句“我想随遇而安地度过余生”，然后抓耳挠腮地度过了三天当时的我的余生，什么也没写下来。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;然后，疫情嘛，研究上的事，能在家里做的已经做得差不多了。闲来无事翻翻邮件订阅的论文摘要合辑，看到了一篇讲量子态马尔科夫演化的论文，于是想到了一个很有趣的问题：人生是一个马尔科夫过程吗？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;先等一下，马尔科夫过程是什么？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;用一个生活中的例子来解释吧。假设我们有一个感兴趣的对象（比如说我现在使用的牙膏的牌子）；这个对象有几种不同的可能性（我去的超市里有两种牌子，我可以但也只能选择其中的一种）；每过一段时间，这个对象有可能变化（每管牙膏用完之后，去超市再买一管，要么换牌子，要么不换）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;重点来了：如果当我在货架面前考虑要买哪个牌子牙膏的时候，只考虑我现在用的是什么牌子，而不考虑上次买牙膏之前那管是什么牌子，不考虑之前任何一段时间用的是什么牌子，那么我使用的牙膏的牌子随时间的变化，就是一个马尔科夫过程。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;也就是维基百科上所说的：“未来的状态与任何历史的状态无关，仅与当前状态相关”。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这么一说的话，人生还真的挺像是马尔科夫过程的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今天认识我的朋友可能想象不出来，我小学的时候还是个很听话的乖孩子。坐我后桌的小豪也很听话，班主任很信任我们几个孩子，经常让我们帮忙干点活儿，平时考试之后改改卷子啊，上面下来检查之前收拾收拾同学们的作业之类的。六年级下学期的某一天，老师放学后又把我们几个人留了下来，给了我们一叠材料，仔细一看，有一摞表格，上面是全班同学姓名和家庭住址的表格，前几天发给每个人回家填了，第二天连同房产证一起交上，房产证很快发回来了，表格在这；还有一张本市本区的地图，道路标的还挺详细的，道路围成的方块上标着不同的数字。我们的任务就是根据家庭住址，把大家的名字和地图上的数字对应起来，填到一张新表上。我和小豪的家有点距离，在地图上的数字也不一样。等我们拿到了不同初中的录取通知书，才后知后觉，当初那些数字代表的就是所谓的学区。高中之后骑车上学，有天早晨，在到校之前的最后一个路口等红灯的时候，眼睛余光觉得旁边等灯的人老是看我，我也看过去，端详许久，是小豪！我们都长出了一口气，不知道是舒气还是叹气。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因为一个学区号，原本要好的朋友再相见，就只能努力注视然后努力回忆，再报以礼貌的微笑了；因为一场中考，因为一场高考，因为考研或是考公务员或是招聘面试，三年、四年、几十年的时间里，我们能做的事情就大体定下来了。至于在这决定未来的考试之前的每一个平凡一天里，我们的生活充实吗，枯燥吗，快乐吗，累吗，见到许久未见的老朋友了吗，不好意思，不太重要。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;所以说，把人生当成一个马尔科夫过程的话，一个很自然的推论就是，我只要在这些时间节点上，让自己拥有这些节点所考察的那些成绩，就可以在人生这条长河里一路顺风顺水，幸福美满了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;大一结束的暑假，我们班的导师老史带我们去北京参观几个科研院所，用他的原话说，“见见世面”。从正负电子对撞机里出来的时候是下午，还有点时间，我们就去了北大。北大接待我们的老师是我们热学课本的作者，那是我第一次亲眼见到写教材的人，一种“我也见到大人物了”的自豪感油然而生。这样的参观活动本来也有为将来的保研做广告的意思，作者老师把我们引入一间教室，拿出了准备好的幻灯片。北大嘛，客观地指点指点江山就足以作为广告了。江山指点得差不多了，还没有看到我们学校的名字，老师大约也注意到了：“你们学校啊，还是差了一点。”老史也和我们坐在一起，除了点头也说不出话来。又有同学问，既然已经有这么大的差距了，那该怎么弥补呢？老师面带微笑地说：“人生啊还是很长的，你们现在虽然落后很多，但是一直努力的话，比别人晚个几年十几年，也是有希望达到同样高度的嘛。”我当时自然心里一百个不服，拳头在桌子后面攥得紧紧的。临走的时候，作者老师还问了一句：“我那本课本是写给非专业的课程用的，你们专业用这个，是不是浅了一点啊？”我很幸运，没看到史老师脸上的表情。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;反过来说，只要在某一个时间节点上没有做好，之后的人生就可以洗洗睡了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但是，人生也并不总是能简化成马尔科夫过程的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;乔布斯在斯坦福大学的毕业典礼上做过一个演讲，讲过他读书时候的故事。领养乔布斯的夫妻当初答应了他的生母，一定要让孩子上大学。乔布斯年轻时也不知道父母的艰难，选了里德学院这样一所学费高昂的私立学校，很快就把父母给的钱花光了，只能退学。退学之后没有了学分要求，他得以选一些轻松有趣的课程，比如字体设计。等到后来兜兜转转，他被苹果公司开除，成功建立了 Pixel 动画公司和 NeXT 电脑公司，之后回到了经营不善来到破产边缘的苹果。这时候，之前的字体课派上了用场，苹果的新电脑取得了巨大的成功，优雅的字体居功至伟。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;人生并不是一个预先设计好的程序，也不是一台严丝合缝的机器，我们经历过的故事，有的深藏在记忆里，在不经意的时候闪现，击中我们；有的成为心中高悬的苦胆，时时提醒激励着人，去做一些可能徒劳但又不甘心的事情。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;北大的故事其实没有结束。当初提问该如何奋起直追的同学转到了数学专业，而一直志在生物的我反而留在了物理圈里。大四的时候，听说北大一个物理和生物的交叉学科项目还有一次补充录取的机会，申请美国学校结果不太满意的我就报了名。面试的一个环节是读一段英文学术论文的节选，然后根据材料回答几个问题。我抽到的文章是关于 microbiome （微生物组）的，老师们知道我的专业背景，本来没打算我回答得出什么问题，没想到我平时读过一些科普文章，对这个话题有些了解，老师的问题都很顺利地回答了出来。他们很意外，问我是怎么积累这些知识的，我很想给他们讲讲三年前那个下午，隔壁系教室里的故事。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;又觉得什么也不必讲，于是微笑着谦虚了两句。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/how-to-spend-life</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">mountaye.github.io/blog/articles/how-to-spend-life</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
